<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine vvayes for the ordering of souldiours in battelray, and setting of battayles, after diuers fashions with their manner of marching: and also fugures [sic] of certayne newe plattes for fortification of townes: and moreover, howe to make saltpeter, gunpouder and diuers sortes of fireworkes or wilde fyre, with other thinges appertayning to the warres. / Gathered &amp; set foorth by Peter Whitehorne.</title>
            <author>Whithorne, Peter, fl. 1550-1563.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 155KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B36534</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">48553594_176553</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176553</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248525861</idno>
  <idno type="STC">Other 4539</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S492274</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B36534)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176553)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 312:5b or 431:5b)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine vvayes for the ordering of souldiours in battelray, and setting of battayles, after diuers fashions with their manner of marching: and also fugures [sic] of certayne newe plattes for fortification of townes: and moreover, howe to make saltpeter, gunpouder and diuers sortes of fireworkes or wilde fyre, with other thinges appertayning to the warres. / Gathered &amp; set foorth by Peter Whitehorne.</title>
                  <author>Whithorne, Peter, fl. 1550-1563.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[107] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by VV. VVilliamson: for Ihon VVight.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1573.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>This item is not in STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>With: The arte of warre, written in Italian by Nicholas Machiauel, and set foorth in English by Peter Withorne, studient at Graies Inne: with other like martiall feates and experiments, as in a table in the ende of the booke may appeare -- Most briefe tables to knovv redily hovv manie ranckes of footemen armed with corslettes, as vnarmed, go to the making of a iust battaile.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Military art and science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Artillery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Military fireworks.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Gunpowder.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176553:1"/>
            <p>❧ <hi>CERTAINE vvayes for the ordering of <hi>Souldiours in battelray, and setting</hi>
               </hi> of battayles, after diuers fashions, with their maner of marching: And also Fugures of certayne newe plattes for fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Townes: And more ouer, howe to make Saltpeter, Gunpouder, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers sortes of Fireworkes or wilde Fyre, with other thinges ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayning to the warres. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered &amp; set foorth by <hi>Peter VVhitehorne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London by <hi>VV. VVilliamson: for Ihon VVight.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno. 1573.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:176553:2"/>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:176553:2"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>A perfecte rule to bring men into</hi> a square battell, of what number so euer they be. Cap. i.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or to make a square Battell</hi> of a number of men, or of an Armie, the fowresquare roote or Quadrante number of them, muste be taken, and so manye as the same roote contaynes, so manye oughte to be set in araye. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in a littell number, for the better vnderstanding thereof: Admitte there be a .100. men, the Fowresquare roote of .100. ought to be taken oute, which is tenne: Then putting tenne of these men in a rancke, there will be tenne ranckes, ten to a rancke. Whiche tenne ranckes placing them or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarylye, the one behinde the other, so that all the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances that shall be betwene man and man, as well on the sides, as before and behinde be equall, suche .100. menne will make a fowresquare battaile, as by the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure here following appeareth.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of a square battle</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label" cols="12">Head</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label" rows="10">Flancke</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell role="label" rows="10">Flancke</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:176553:3"/>
               <p>But for that men ordered in battelraye, stande not, nor marche not, as aboue is supposed, I meane in equall distaunce, for that euery man (as Vegetius affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth) would haue for largenesse thrée foote, that is from shoulder to shoulder, and for lengthe séeuen foote, that is thrée foote before him, and thrée foote behinde him, and one foote that his owne person will occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pye, for whiche cause the aboue written order, menne standing according to the sayde ordinarye, distaunce, shall not be a iuste fowresquare, but the lengthe thereof shalbe .70. foote, and the bredthe .30. foote, as appeareth by the figure following.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of a square formation, 27 ranks of 3 men</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label" cols="10">Flancke</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell role="label" rows="10">Head</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label" cols="10">Flancke</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
               </figure>
               <p>And where some number of men commethe not after suche sorte to bée fowresquare, as .200. the roote whereof is .14. althoughe there bée .4. ouerplus: in this case there ought to be put fouretene in a ranke, &amp; the sayd battaile will come neuerthelesse to be foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>square: That is, it shall be of .14. ranckes of menne 14. to a rancke, and as for those fowre menne that are ouerplus out of the araye, the Sergant maye place eyther in the taile thereof, or elles where séemes him best oute of that order:</p>
               <p>Likewise after this manner, an army of men howe greate a number so euer it bée, maye be broughte into a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:176553:3"/> fowresquare, as for example, admitte there were an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye of .35000. of these .35000. menne, the fowresquare roote is to be taken oute, according to the order that I haue declared before, and the same shall be founde to be .187. and .31. menne remayning ouerplus, so that placing .187. menne in a rancke, suche an armye will be in fashion fowresquare, that is, it will amounte vnto 187. ranckes .187. menne for a rancke. And as for the .31 odde men, the Capitaine may appoinctte where he shall thincke good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ To knowe howe many men maye marche in a rancke, and at a sudden to bring them into a fowresquare battaile, so that their Ansigne, may come to be in the middest. Cap. 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or to doo this thing with speede, the</hi> fowresquare roote of what number of menne so euer it be, is straighte waye to be taken: and if the same roote be so that it maye be equally deuided into thrée, so many as shall be the thirde parte of that roote, so many of the saide menne for a rancke oughte to marche by the waye. As for example, if the men that are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted, be .81. the roote of those .81. muste be taken, the which is .9. And for as muche as the roote of this may equallye be deuided into .3. and the thirde parte there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of being .3. the sayde .s1. menne must therefore be made to marche in iorneing thrée in a rancke, and they shall make in all .27. ranckes, as here vnder appereth.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of 27 ranks of 3 men</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>c</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>a</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label" rows="3">Tayle</cell>
                           <cell>o o o o o o o o o</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o o o o o o o o o</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o o o o o o o o o</cell>
                           <cell role="label" rows="3">Head</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o o o o o o o o o</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o o o o o o o o o</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o o o o o o o o o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o o o o o o o o o</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o o o o o o o o o</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o o o o o o o o o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>d</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>b</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
               </figure>
               <p>And when néede is that they muste bée broughte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a fouresquare battaile, all these 27. ranckes would be
<pb facs="tcp:176553:4"/> deuided into thrée equall partes, as is declared by <hi>a b.</hi> and <hi>c d.</hi> So that to euery parte there come to remayne 9. ranckes, thrée men in a rancke, and afterwarde the firste parte that is in the Fronte must be caused to stay, and the other twaine to procede forewarde, the one on the righte hande, and the other on the lefte hande of the firste (now standing still) vntill the headde or Fronte of eyther of the saide twoo partes doo vnite or come to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with the headde of the firste, and there to stay. As by the figure following may be vnderstoode.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of containing 27 ranks of 3 men divided in 3 parts</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell role="label" rows="9">Fronte.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell cols="2">A</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
               </figure>
               <p>The whiche thrée partes thus broughte and ordered, shall make a fowresquare battaile, as appearethe by this figure following: and to cause that the Ansigne doo fall in the middest of suche a battaile, alwayes it oughte to be placed in the middest of the firste parte, as before appeareth in the poincte. <hi>A.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of previous 3 parts brought and ordered into a square battalion with the flag standard in the center</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label" cols="9">Head</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>A</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                           <cell>o</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
               </figure>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:176553:4"/>
               <p>But to knowe howe to deuide the sayde .27. ranckes into thrée equall portions without standing to tell nyne ranckes, considering that if it were a great nomber of men, it should be a thing very long so to do: therfore séeing that to euery nomber of men, there is commonly placed a rancke of Harkabutters or Bowemen in the Forewarde, &amp; an other in the Rerewarde, in this figure aboue written of foure score men and one, there would bée .18. Harkabutters: that is 9. in the Forewarde, and 9. in the Rereward: and setting twoo ranckes of Harka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butters in the places where y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> deuisions are to bée made, as hereafter appeareth in figure, vnderstanding the Harkabutters by this letter <hi>H.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of 27 ranks of 3 men divided into 3 parts by harquebusiers</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o A o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
               </figure>
               <p>By those Harkabutters you maye alwayes vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande where the diuisions are to be made of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sayd 27. ranckes, and likewise in euerye other greater nomber. And when suche a roote cannot bée deuided into thrée e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall partes, of necessitie there must remayne ouer one or twoo. Now let vs firste take for example this, where remayneth ouer one, as it shoulde bée if it were a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred men, the roote whereof is tenne, which tenne deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into thrée, commeth to thrée times thrée, and one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning ouerplus. Wherefore there muste bée made tenne ranckes to march thrée and thrée (that is so many rankes as the nomber of the roote is of) and other tenne ranckes foure &amp; foure together, and the last .10. ranckes also thrée &amp; thrée together: as here folowing appeareth with their 20. Harkabutters or Bowemen, besides the saide hundred men.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of 100 men divided into 11 ranks of 3, 11 ranks of 4, 11 ranks of 3 with harquebusiers in between</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell role="label" rows="7">Front</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:176553:5"/>
               <p>And these thrée partes when it is néedefull to bring them into a fowresquare battaile, muste be ordered as aboue is rehearsed, or elles causing the first parte in the Forewarde to staye, and to make the second part to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede onwarde vntill the heade or fronte of the seconde parte come to be euen with the headde of the first, and so the saide seconde part standing still, to cause also y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> third parte to procede forewarde after the same maner, the which thing béeing done, such a battaile shalbe broughte into fashion fowresquare, with their Harkabutters or Bowemen before &amp; behind: as appeareth by this figure.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of the 100 men and harquebusiers in square formation with the flag standard in the middle</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label" rows="11">Backe</cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell role="label" rows="11">Head</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>A</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
               </figure>
               <p>But when in deuiding the sayde roote there shall happen to remaine .2. ouerplus, as should be when there were .121. the roote whereof is .11. whiche .11. perting into .3. comes to .3. times .3. and twoo remayning ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus (as I haue sayde) in this case and in other like, I woulde make a .11. ranckes to marche (that is, as many as the roote containes) .4. menne in a rancke, and an other .11. ranckes .3. menne together in a rancke, and the other .11. ranckes also .4. menne to a rancke: As hereafter appeareth in figure, with their .22. Harkabutters, beside the saide .121. menne.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of 121 men divided into 11 ranks of 4, 11 ranks of 3, 11 ranks of 4 with harquebusiers between them</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>H o o o o o o o o o o o H</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
               </figure>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:176553:5"/>
               <p>The whiche men alwayes, when they woulde be brought into a fowresquare battell, muste be ordered as before is declared.</p>
               <p>And this rule may serue likewyse in what littell or greate number so euer it be, as well quadrante as not quadrante. As for example onely in wordes: put the case that there bée .3969. whereof being minded to know how many mē in a rācke shold be caused to march togethers by the waye, so that commodiouslye they maye at a so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, bée broughte into a fowresquare battell, then must be taken the quadrante roote of this number of menne (by the same waye that I haue taughte) whiche shall be founde to be .63. so that on euery side of the square bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell shall be .63. ranckes of menne, and for as muche as this roote (whiche is .63) maye be deuided into .3. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall partes, the thirde parte thereof is to be taken (for a generall rule) that is .21. and therefore .21. menne in a rancke woulde be made to marche togethers by the waye. And alwaies there shall be as many ranckes in all after .21. to a rancke, as are thrée times so manye as the roote is of, whiche is, thrée times .63. whiche comes to 189. so that .189. ranckes of men shal be the number ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of after .21. to a rancke. And by the roote that is .63. you may vnderstande that suche deuision is to be made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene .63. and .63. so y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the firste shall be as well .63. part as also the seconde and the thirde. In whiche deuisions the twoo double ranckes of Harkabutters are to be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for the redier knowledge to bring them into a square battell. But if in deuiding the roote into thrée, there shoulde remayne .1. ouerplus, as shoulde happen if the presupposed men were .5776. the roote whereof being 76. whiche roote deuided into .3. shall come vnto .25. and one to remayne ouerplus. Nowe I saye, that all the ranckes that riseth of these men, shall be notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thrée times so manye as the roote, that is three times .76. which makes .228. And for as muche as all
<pb facs="tcp:176553:6"/> these orders of ranckes, are deuided euermore into .3. partes (as before hath bene declared) .76. ranckes to ā parte (that is so many as the roote is of) therefore it is to be vnderstande, that the firste and the laste of these thrée partes muste bee made to marche .25. men in a rancke, whiche is as muche as is the thirde parte of the roote, and for that there remayneth one ouerplus (as aboue appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth) I saye that the same one muste bée put alwaies in the seconde parte, whiche is in the middeste, I meane causing those of the saide seconde parte, to marche .26. menne in a rancke, so that the firste and the last part of the greate rewe of ranckes, be .25. men in a rancke, and the second parte to bée .26. men in a rancke, and the very same ought to be done of euery other roote that may be deuided into thrée, where onely remaineth ouerplus one but when there remainethe ouerplus .2. it followeth, cleane contrary: For that the firste and the laste parte would be of one mā more, thē the same that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> third part of the roote is of. As for example if the saide men were 2809. the roote whereof is .53. whiche deuided into thrée, coomes to .71. and .2. remayning ouerplus: therefore of so many menne, there shall bée made .159. ranckes (that is thrée times .53.) whiche .159. ranckes deuiding them also into thrée partes commeth vnto .53. to a parte, that is the number of the roote. And the firste and thirde parte woulde be of one man more then the thirde parte of the roote, that is, it would be of .18. menne to a rancke, and the seconde parte, whiche is the parte in the middest, woulde be the verye thirde parte of the roote: that is, 17. menne to a rancke, so that of all the .159. ranckes, as wel the first .53. ranckes, as likewise the last .53. ranckes oughte to be of .18, men to a rancke, and the .53. ranckes in the middeste woulde be onely of .17. men to a rancke And, wherein parting the roote into .3. there remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethe ouerplus onelye one, it goeth cleane contrarye to this. For that the fyrste and the thirde parte of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:176553:6"/> sayde great rew of ranckes, will alwaies be of as many men to a rancke as shalbe the whole thirde parte of the roote, and the middle parte, whiche is the second, will bee of one man more then the thirde parte of the roote. And for as muche, as there can neuer remayne ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus aboue one or twoo in deuiding the roote into thrée, therfore this foresayde rule shall serue in what nomber of men so euer it bée, as well Quadrante as not Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drante, for that like as before is sayde in nombers not Quadrante, alwayes there is taken the roote whiche goeth néerest to suche a nomber, and therewith to do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, as aboue hath bene sayed. And as for the resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of the men that cōmeth to be ouerplus of the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drante of such a roote, maye be placed some other where as shall be thoughte moste beste. For example if there were foure thousande men, which nomber is not Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drante, yet notwithstanding of the same nomber there oughte to be taken oute the néerest roote therof, whiche is lxiii. so that there shall remayne ouerplus one and thirtie men, whome minding in a suddaine to bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a fouresquare battayle, there oughte to be putte in a rancke. lxiii. men, and suche a battayle shall come to bée fowersquare, as in the beginning hath béene sayde: and where there remaynes ouerplus those .31. men, the Sergiant may place thē as he shal thinke good. Likewise minding to cause those 4000. men to march, there ought also to be taken the néerest roote therof, which as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayde, is .63. which deuiding into thrée, comes vnto thrée times 21. &amp; nothing remayning ouerplus. And therefore the sayde men ought to bée caused to marche .xxi. in a ranke, &amp; the sayde rancke to be deuided into thrée parts. lxiii. to a rancke according to the foresayde rule, in suche sorte that the last parte shalbe .64. ranckes, and also .10. men more because of those .31. men that were ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus in the beginning, the whiche as hathe béene sayde remayned oute of the araye: And after the same maner,
<pb facs="tcp:176553:7"/> it is to be done when the roote of such a number that is not quadrante, dooth not agrée with the perfecte deuision by thrée, which is, if there be ouerplus one, to procede as aboue hath bene declared. I meane to put a man more in a rancke to the middell parte, and to the other twoo partes, the first, and the third, to put onely so many men in a rancke, as the thirde paite of the roote shal conteine, and when there remaineth ouerplus twoo, to procede cleane contrary: that is, to put a man more in a rancke to the firste, and to the thyrde parte, and to the seconde, to put onelye so manye men in a rancke as the thirde parte of the roote shall bée of, and those men that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning ouerplus, in taking out the roote in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, to place them as aboue I haue saide.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Howe to ordayne a nomber of men or an armie into a battayle, like vnto a wedge, or three square, so that it maye be apte to marche with the poincte thereof to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the enemies. Cap. 3.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His fashion of battayle, is made after this maner, first placing one man, and after thrée, and nexte fiue, and after seuen, and then .9. after a .11. &amp; so to increase awaies twoo men more, till suche time as there bee no more men to place. Albeit there maye be such a nomber of men, that at the last they can not, or there shall not be sufficient to make vp the last rancke, which hapning, those men may be left out of the araye to serue wher their captain shal thinke most meete, for y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the like hapneth often times, and in euerye maner of ordering men, that alwayes there resteth some man out of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray. And for the better vnderstanding hereof: admit for example that the men that is to bée brought into a thrée
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176553:7"/> square battaile bée a .100. I saye that firste one is to bée placed, after .3. after 5, after .7. after .9. after .11. and so to proceade: adding alwayes twoo men more in a rancke, vntill they bée all placed, as here following appeareth in figure. Where the last rancke in this case, shall come to bée 19. men, not remayning anye man ouerplus: and this is, for that the number of men, (whiche is .100.) is a Quadrante nomber: and likewise in euery other nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that is Quadrante, the sayde Triangle battaile shal bée made withoute any man remayning ouerplus.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of 100 men in a wedge formation</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>But if the sayde nomber of men bée not a quadrante nomber alwayes there shall remayne ouerplus so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye men, as the sayde nomber of men shall bee more then the great quadrant nomber contained of the same: as for example, if the presuposed men to make the thrée square battell were .120. I saye that there shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne ouerplus .20. men oute of the aray of the thrée square, that is so manye as the .120. exceadeth .100. (being the greater Quadrante nomber contayned in the same) whiche also shall bée .20. but if the sayde men were .123. there shoulde remayne ouerplus only twoo men, for as muche as the greatest quadrant nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:176553:8"/> that can be taken of .123. shall be .121. and .123. is more then the saide .121. by the saide twoo, and the verye same is to be vnderstand in euery greate number.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>¶</hi> To make the battell called the sheeres, whiche in olde time they vsed to set against the Triangle. Cap. 4.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Sheeres are made with</hi> twoo Triangles ioygned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gethers, for to receiue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wene them the saide battell, made like a wedge or Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle. The example where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I wil make also with .100. men, as the Triangle or wedge was made, so that thereby maye be iudged if there were twoo armies of equall numbers of menne, and that the one of them were pitched like a Triangle, and the other like a Shéeres, which of them should haue the aduauntage. Wherefore minding of .100. men to make the battell called the Shéeres, they oughte to be deuided into twoo equall partes, and of euerye one of these partes being .50. to make a Triangle according to the maner aboue declared, and to ioigne them together, as here folowing appeareth in figure with their poinctes towardes the enemies: I meane towardes the wedge, to receiue it betwene them: And it is to be nooted how in making of these twoo Triangles, there shal remaine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerplus one man of euery one of them out of the araye, for that the number of .50. is no Quadrant number, and it is more then the Quadrante number contained of the same (whiche is .46. by a man onely) so that betwene them bothe, there shall remaine ouerplus twoo men, as here appeareth in Figure.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:176553:8"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of a Sheeres formation opposing a wedge formation</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>VVhat auantage it is to order men in a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle battaile against the enemy that knoweth not how to make the battaile called the Shree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res to set against it, inespecially where there is as many men of the one part as of the other. Cap. 5.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the contrarie parte woulde come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst a threesquare battayle, with a bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle that were fouresquare, as nowe a dayes is vsed, by all reason it shalbe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and ouerthrowne. As admit for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample that there bée 100. in a thréesquare battayle, &amp; a hundred other men in a fouresquare battaile, pitched a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> iii. square, as here folowing appeareth in figure.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:176553:9"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of a wedge formation opposing a rectangular formation</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>And for that the order of the Triangle in fighting, is after suche sorte, that all those whiche shoote with anye kinde of weapon, as péeces of Ordinaunce, Harkabuses Dartes, Bowes, or Crosbowes, oughte all to directe their shotte, and to strike only in the same place, where the poincte of the Triangle séekes to enter, I meane in in the poincte <hi>A.</hi> whereby the men that are in the same place, shall either bée slayne or else constrayned to geue place to the poincte of the sayde Triangle throughe the great multitude of shotte striking in that place. So that the poincte of the sayde Triangle entering therin, maye continually penetrate al the sayde aray cleane through. For as much as all the Harkabutters, &amp; Archers which remayne without, must not cease to shoote in the verye same place, &amp; no other where else: whiche thing doing it is impossible but that waye shall bée giuen for the sayde Triangle to enter in, and once entred, suche an armye is ouerthrowen without anye reméedye. For all the force and strength of suche a Triangle being
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:176553:9"/> made in that place onely, it is not possible that men in suche a place may be able to withstand, althoughe there were many more in suche Quadrante aray, then those that be in the saide Triangle, because the place of. <hi>A</hi> cannot be succoured of any of those of the same battell, considering that if those which are placed towardes. <hi>B.</hi> or elles towardes. <hi>C.</hi> woulde come to succour the place where the violence and force is made, it must néedes be, that they must disorder them selues: and being once dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered, they runne into the very same mischiefe, after suche sorte, that they shall remaine altogether broken: and remaining in their places, their strength or power, resteth of none effecte: for as much as none of them can be able to doo any thing, howe valiaunte soeuer he be.</p>
               <p>Whereby may be vnderstoode of what importance this Triangle battell is againste the enemie, that knowethe not the medesin or remedy thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>¶</hi> To bring a number of men or an armie, into a batell, which in olde time was called a Sawe. Cap. 6.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His fashiō of Battel according to the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the name, oughte to bée made is it were with téethe, like vnto a Sawe whiche they vse to Sawe timber with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. And therefore minding to bring a number of men, or an armie into suche a fashion, there muste be considered twoo thinges, the one, howe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny téethe, this Sawe is to be made of, and whether be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides those téethe, there woulde be anye other raies to sustaine suche teethe or no. As for example, admit that the men of whome muste be made those onely téethe of this foresayde Sawe, be .100. nowe these .100. menne oughte to be deuided into the number of the teethe that this Saw shall haue, and of euery of one those parts,
<pb facs="tcp:176553:10"/> to fashion a Triangle, by the Rule declared in the thirde Chapter: and those Triangels to ioyne close toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, according as was done of those twoo that made the Shéeres: As put case that of the sayde hundred men there woulde be made foure téeth of a Sawe, then the sayde .100. men muste bée deuided in to foure partes, in whiche deuisions it will come to 25. for a parte. Nowe of euery one of these partes, there ought to be fashioned a Triangle, according to the order geuen in the forsaide thirde Chapter. And these foure Triangles to ioyne them straight together, as here following appeareth in figure: and this is in as much as in making the téeth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye: but if peraduenture there woulde be put an other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der behinde the sayde foure téeth, it is néedefull firste to determine of how many men such a raye is to be made, and those to take oute by them selues, and of the rest to<figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of a saw formation</figDesc>
                  </figure> make the téeth, and behinde the sayde téeth to place those nomber of men whiche first were taken oute, and to ordayne them so manye men in a rancke, as shall bée founde directlye in length in all the hinder partes of the téeth that are made, as for example, admitte there bée twoo hundred &amp; xliiij. men, and that with a hundred men therof, there must be made foure téeth of a Sawe, &amp; the other 144. to be made certayne ranckes to sustayne the sayde foure téeth: Therefore the hundred men being broughte into foure téeth, as aboute is declared, conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently behinde those 5 there oughte to bée placed those C. &amp; xliiii. men. xxxvi. mē to a ranke: for as much as in all the foure lower partes of the sayde foure téethe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:176553:10"/> there bée 36. men as in the figure nexte following ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth. And after this maner and order, if there were a hundred thousande men, they mighte bée set in a raye, placing them, as aboue is done with that litle nomber.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of a saw formation with replacement ranks</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ To fashion a battayle of a nomber of men or an armie like vnto twoo Triangles ioyned together, so that they may bee apte to marche with a corner therof towarde the enemies. Cap. 7.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith the rule whereby the single Triangle is</hi> made, with the verie same almost this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion battayle is also made: for as muche as deuiding all those men, or that Armye wherewith this fashion battayle is made into twoo equall partes, and of the one halfe thereof to make a Triangle, and that done, vpon the very last side of the same, there ought to be placed the other halfe nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of men in ranckes, which continually go decreasing by twoo mē lesse, I meane cleane cōtrarie to y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> was done at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> beginning with one, where beginning to make the poincte of the Triangle, the ranckes were continuallye increased with twoo men more. But it is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande, that if in making the first Triāgle, there happen
<pb facs="tcp:176553:11"/> to remaine ouerplus any men, that are not sufficient to make vp an other rancke, yet the very same rancke oughte to be finished vp with some of the other halfe nū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of men, for that one of these twoo Triangles ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together, commeth to be of one rancke more then the other. As for example, admit the men, wherewith this fashion battell is to bée made, be .320. which muste be deuided into twoo equall partes, so that by suche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uision there wyll be .160. men for a parte, and of the one of these partes, there woulde bée made a Triangle, according to the order declared in the thirde Chapiter, whiche doone, there shall be founde to remayne ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus .16. (by the reason aledged in the saide third Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) so that there shall lacke .9. men to finishe the saide laste rancke of the first Triangle: Therefore the saide rancke muste bée made vp, with the men of the other halfe, as taking those .19. men whiche lackes, so that in the saide firste Triangle maye be .169. men, and in the other parte onelye .151. menne, wherewith the other Triangle ought to bée made vpon the laste rancke of the firste, whiche laste rancke shall be of .25. men: wherefore vpon the same, there muste be placed an other rancke of twoo men lesse, that is .23. and vppon the same saide .23. menne, to place an other of .21. menne, and vpon the .21. mene, to place an other of .19. menne, and vpon those .19. men, to place an other of .17. men, and so to procede al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes with twoo men lesse, till suche time as it cometh to the rancke of one man onely, as here folowing appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in figure: Trew it is, that there shall be founde in the ende, to remaine ouerplus .7. men, the whiche the Sargiant maye place where he shall thincke good. And thus with this maner of order, there may be brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to like araye, anie armie howe greate so euer it be, and they may turne them selues, and in marching, make of the Rerewarde, the Forewarde, and likewyse of what so euer side they liste.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:176553:11"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of two wedge formations joined into a diamond formation</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:176553:12"/>
               <head>¶ VVhat is best to be done where the ordinance of the enemies being shotte into the army hath slaine many men. Cap. 8.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N Armye of menne that happeneth to haue certaine ranckes thereof to be stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken downe &amp; kilde with the enemies or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce, and marching after such sorte, leauing voide the places of those menne whiche are slaine with the Artillerye, or els drawing thēselues close altogether, to fil such empty places, the one of these waies is very euill, and the other much worse: for as muche as leauing those places after such sort open, inespecially in the foreward, there is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thereby greate faciletie vnto the enemies to enter into the saide raies, and to ouerthrowe them. And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise causing after such misfortune y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saide raies to draw together, to fill the saide places, those raies must néedes altogether be disordered; and shall bée broughte almoste into confusion: for y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it is to be thoughte that the saide ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery, dothe not destroye any rancke of menne wholye from one ende to an other in lengthe, but onelye a parte of some, and a parte of other, and some to remaine vntouched, or vnhurte. In whiche case be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing minded to cause them to drawe together, to fill vp the sayde voide places, it muste néedes followe that the whole rancke doo disorder in lengthing those that lacke, so that some of the ranckes shall remaine withe a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number of ranckes of menne (in length) in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewarde, then in the Forewarde, whereby if such a bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell woulde Marche of necessitye it will immediatelye run into confusion, because of those ranckes that are vnperfecte in lengthe, Wherefore that Capitaine, is to bée praised, whiche instructethe his menne that in like chaunces, they neuer remaine withoute a compaigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before them, excepte it be in the Fronte, as to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertise
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:176553:12"/> euerye one of them, that if fortune to happen anye of them to lacke the same man, whiche was wonte to marche before them, or elles mo, that then incontinente, and with selerette they doo marche for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, vntill they finde an other companion in the accustomed distaunce before them, and where it fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethe noo man to be founde, to aduertise them, howe they shoulde then procéede till they come to the head or Fronte, and in such place to stand still, or elles to march according as the other ranckes in the headde or in the Fronte shall doo. And this being a generall rule that euerye man muste take the measure of his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng softelye or faste of his compaignions that gooeth before him, and not of anye that be of theyr sides. All those menne therefore that shall be founde in the verye same rancke behinde suche a man that dooeth lacke his compaignion or compaignions before him, shall bée constrained to runne, or goo a pase according as that man shall marche, whiche shall bée nexte before him: whiche thing being obserued of euerye man in the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, alwayes the Forewarde or Fronte thereof, shall come thereby to be whole and sounde, and those emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie places of the deade to be transeformed into the Rere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, in whiche places there shall not almoste be any perrill. As for example, admitte, that in a battell of 144. menne in fashion fowresquare, the enemies hath slaine .12. menne, as by the voide places in the figure folowing appearethe, I saye that hauing aduertised euerye man to doo as muche as before I haue declared, whiche is, that euerye time that he lackethe his fellowe (or moo men) that marched before him, he doo straighte waye make haste, and withe all spéede possible not to seace going forewarde, till he finde an other compaig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb facs="tcp:176553:13"/> in the accustomed distaunce that goeth before him.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of a square formation missing soldiers in the front</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>And if it fortune in suche a rancke that in the ende hée finde no man, yet he ought to proceade so muche till hée come to the last ranke in the Front, and there to stande still, or els to marche according to the order of the saide rancke. And likewise euery man ought to take héede that in his marching faste or softelye, hée doo rule him selfe by his compaignion that goeth before him, and not of any of those that be on his sides: which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176553:13"/> thing being obserued, as in the figured rayes aboue<figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of a square formation missing soldiers in the back</figDesc>
                  </figure> written, they same battales, shal be transformed in this other maner, like vnto the last figure, that is, those 12. voide places shalbe translated into the reward, as plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye maye be séene.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ How to chaunge with speede an Armie, that is, in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telray fouresquare, into a triangell fashiō, without dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordering the first ranckes, and without perill of confusion. Cap. xix.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:176553:14"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ike as the Capitaine with sounde of the Trompette, or with voyce shall cause the Souldiours to be aduertised and taughte to knowe howe to turne that waye, which is betwene the fronte and the righte side, or the lefte, and likewyse that waye that is betwene the righte, or lefte side, and the backe, and after that they shall bée well informed therin, euen so I would also haue thē to be well aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tised of the same, that was declared in the laste chapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whiche is to shewe and teache euery man, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes when he shall be caused to turne towardes anye of the foresaide sides, and shall not finde to haue his fellowe in the accustomed distance before him, that then the same man with all spéede doo procede, or march so farre righte forthe, till he finde a companion before him in the accustomed distaunce: Of whiche thing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery souldiour being well informed and instructed, with the twinkling of an eye, an Armye that is in fashion .iiij. square, may be transeformed into a triangle. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, minding to make the right corner y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> poinct of the sayd triangle, with sounde of Trumpette, or with voice, causing euerye man in the armie to turne them selues with theyr faces that waie, which is betwene the front and the righte flancke, and incontinente, so soone as they are turned, euery man obseruing the foresayd or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that is, that all those, whiche shall perceyue not to haue his fellowe before him in the accustomed distance, doo procede straighte foorthe vntill he haue one, whiche done, the saide fowresquare fashion, shalbe founde to be chaunged into a triangle fashion, and the poincte of the same triangle figure, shall come to bée the righte cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the fronte of the firste figure. Whiche thing, is as easie to be doone as is possible: for the triall where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, let there be for example <hi>.25.</hi> men standing in fashion fowre square, as hereafter appeareth in figure, and to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176553:14"/> cause it to be better vnderstande, I haue thought good to make this figure with the <hi>25.</hi> letters of the a b c. Now minding to chaunge this foure square figure, into a triangell figure, it is néedefull to cause thē all to tourne<figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of a square formation</figDesc>
                     <p>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell role="label" cols="5">Front</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>H</cell>
                              <cell>I</cell>
                              <cell>K</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>L</cell>
                              <cell>M</cell>
                              <cell>N</cell>
                              <cell>O</cell>
                              <cell>P</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>Q</cell>
                              <cell>R</cell>
                              <cell>S</cell>
                              <cell>T</cell>
                              <cell>V</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>X</cell>
                              <cell>Y</cell>
                              <cell>Z</cell>
                              <cell>&amp;</cell>
                              <cell>'</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </p>
                  </figure> with their faces that waye, whiche is betwéene the head and the same side, where I haue thought good to make the poinct of the wedge or triangle: as for example pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing to make the corner. <hi>E.</hi> the poincte and head of the triangle, I shal cause that euery man do tourne with his face that waye, betwéene the front &amp; the righte flancke, towardes the corner. <hi>E.</hi> whiche thing done, the foresayde figure shall come to stande as here appeareth: in whiche figure maye bée séene manye men, that hath no fellowe in the accustome distance before him, although they haue a felow straight before him, much more fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:176553:15"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of the square formation rotating into a diamond formation</figDesc>
                     <p>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell cols="5"> </cell>
                              <cell role="label">Front</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell rows="5"> </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>H</cell>
                              <cell>I</cell>
                              <cell>K</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>L</cell>
                              <cell>M</cell>
                              <cell>N</cell>
                              <cell>O</cell>
                              <cell>P</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>Q</cell>
                              <cell>R</cell>
                              <cell>S</cell>
                              <cell>T</cell>
                              <cell>V</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>X</cell>
                              <cell>Y</cell>
                              <cell>Z</cell>
                              <cell>&amp;</cell>
                              <cell>'</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </p>
                  </figure> of them the ordinarye, whiche is double so muche as the ordinarye, as appeareth by <hi>.F.</hi> whoo hath righte before him <hi>.B.</hi> but the distaunce that is betwene the sayde <hi>.F.</hi> and the saide <hi>.B.</hi> is double so muche as the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarye distaunse, wherefore if <hi>.F.</hi> shall obserue the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes aboue declared, immediately so sone as he shall haue turned his face that waye, he shoulde incontinent goo, to come néerer to the saide <hi>.B.</hi> in the accustomed dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staunce, whiche doing, he shall bring him selfe betwene <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>.G.</hi> Albeit the saide <hi>.G.</hi> shall not remaine in his firste place, but shall goo néerer vnto <hi>.C.</hi> to the accusto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med distaunce, and in the place where <hi>.G.</hi> was firste <hi>L.</hi> muste come. So that <hi>.F.</hi> shall stande betwene <hi>.A.</hi> and <hi>.L,</hi> and likewise if all the other shall procede for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, according to the saide order, vntill euery man finde a fellowe in the accustomed distaunce before him <hi>H.</hi> shall goo néerer vnto <hi>.D.</hi> and <hi>.M.</hi> shall followe the saide <hi>.H.</hi> and <hi>.Q.</hi> shall followe after the saide <hi>.M.</hi> euery one of them, vntill they come to theyr accustomed dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staunce.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:176553:15"/> And in like maner <hi>.I.</hi> shall go néere vnto <hi>.E.</hi> and <hi>N.</hi> shall followe <hi>.I.</hi> and <hi>.R.</hi> shall followe <hi>.N.</hi> and <hi>.X.</hi> shall followe the sayde <hi>.R.</hi> euery one of them vntill they come to their accustomed distaunce. Likewise <hi>.O.</hi> shall go née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to <hi>.K.</hi> and <hi>.S.</hi> shall followe <hi>.O.</hi> and <hi>.Y.</hi> shall followe <hi>.S.</hi> also to the ordinary distaunce: and likewise <hi>.&amp;.</hi> shall also go néerer to <hi>.V.</hi> to the accustomed distaunce, which thing being obserued, such a foure square battel shal be trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into a triangle battell, as here following appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in figure, the poinct whereof shall come to bée the corner <hi>.E.</hi> and with this order a Capitaine may chaunge an armie, with tourning of a hande, though it were of <hi>100000.</hi> men from the fashion of a foure square to the fashion of thréesquare. So that the sayde men be aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tised<figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of the diamond formation changing into a wedge formation</figDesc>
                  </figure> and taughte, as afore hath béene declared, both as well to knowe howe they oughte to tourne as to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che.
<pb facs="tcp:176553:16"/> Whiche is of wonderfull importaunce: for as much, as at a sudden to reduce an armye after this sorte into a triangel fashion, it is almoste impossible that the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies shalbe able, or shall knowe how to make their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie like the Sheres to set against it, wherby shal come great aduauntage as by the <hi>5.</hi> chapitex aboue is plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye prooued: for that it séemes vnto mée that a triangle battayle, maye bee alwaye sufficient able to breake all maner of fouresquare battayles as is vsed now a daies, although it had halfe so many moe men, so long as those of the triangel battel be well instructed of the maner of their fighting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in the v. chapiter.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:176553:16"/>
               <head>¶ Of the perfecte forme or fashion of strong places.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He forme which vnto the</hi> cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular fashion doth moste re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble, of experte and skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full souldiours, is aboue all other with most reason prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, so y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the Curtine or wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les therof, be made straight, and of such length, that of the bulwarkes they may be flāc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: whiche fashion being made with manye corners, is verye méete and necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye if in a sufficient great place it bée erected: for where in small roomes the iuste length of the courtin is shorte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, it is conuenient to buylde them with fewe corners; because if otherwise they shoulde bée shortened with a nomber of corners, the shorter of necessity the spaces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene those muste bée; so that besides that the one bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke maye hurte the other, they shalbe moreouer to no purpose, but rather an occasion of infinite coste, their courtins néeding as is requisit to be defended of platfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and the corners therof shall come to bée lesse blunt, and muche sharper then they oughte to be, by reason of the litle distaunce betwéene them and the platformes.</p>
               <p>Therfore the more that they be made distaunte from those bulwarkes (the due length of the curtin being kept) so much the blunter the corners will come to bée, which by them must be defended, and the more of those corners that there are in the same fashion, so muche the blunter they shall also come to bée. So that where the fashion of the places that are builte bee sufficiente great to contayne all the foresayde particulars, whiche for a sure fortresse is requisite to bée made, all thing commodiously will come to passe: and the greater that
<pb facs="tcp:176553:17"/> they shalbe, the more men they maye haue to defend them and more commodious space within, for to retire with greate and strong fortification, and the platformes maye be made muche further in, and haue the corners of theyr bulwarkes blunt, and with a large backe, méete for defence, and in an assaulte, muche surer then the sharpe, because the sharpe poincted bulwarke, being battered defendeth the enemye from the platformes, so that vnder the same, being couered, he maye almost oute of daunger, make an assaulte. Where against a Towne or Fortresse, that were builte after the fashion of these plattes folowing, in what so euer parte of such places, the enemy should approche marching towardes them to incampe, or in battell raie to assaulte them, or with Trenches, and artillery to batter them, either high or lowe or by the curtin within, or otherwise, he shall alwaies, from many of those flankers of the same place, be greately hurte and repulced, and of the plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes in especially, more then from any other where, because they be moste neere, and stande higher then all the other, and they shall also hurte him more, when he shall bée somewhat farre of, then néere hande, as maye be sene by the plaine platte that hath the number .1. and in the same that is raised vp, that hath the number .2.</p>
               <p>The whiche with twoo other are also here after pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to the ende that thereby maye be considered of such as shall sée them, the sundrye good and notable effectes that bée in them, the whiche althoughe it bée not pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible so easelye with writing to bée expressed, yet by theyr helpe they maye be better vnderstande and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, and moreouer by them shalbe gotten this knowledge, whereby euery man commodiously maye vnderstande, where the enemie gowing aboute with his power, maye best deuise to assaile them, and howe they within maye prouide to defende and withstand the same with theyr men, taking them from those places
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:176553:17"/> where they may best be spared, so y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> building the fashiō of fortresses, in the saide maner, there shall in no place happen any such incommodities, as in other that are ignorauntly made, after the ordinary fashion with lesse corners, as also by these figures, here folowing is more plainlye declared.</p>
               <p>There oughte also to be noted, that these and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther plattes, in this treatise set foorth, being drawen in a litle space, coulde not bée fashioned with their due proportion: albeit to the ende that same which is reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned about them, might partly bée vnderstande, they are not left out or omitted: for without their help it shoulde haue bene impossible for anye man, to haue comprehē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that, which I séeke to declare, concerning fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, although they were expert souldiours: as by the foresayde plattes of the nombre of 1. and 2. maye mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festlye bée séene, howe well the courteynes of suche a towne, is by the bulwarkes therof defended, and howe the ditches of the platformes, and of both of them are flancked and skowred, besides other thinges, whiche by the lines that are drawen be declared, where o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise it coulde not bée shewed after such sorte, as it might bée vnderstande, and the like happeneth in the other.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:176553:18"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of a fortification</figDesc>
                  <p>1 D C B V F H K M O Q S T E G I L N P R</p>
               </figure>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:176553:18"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of a fortification</figDesc>
                  <p>2 G F D O B</p>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:176553:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>¶</hi> The strongest and perfectest fashion of all other for the building of the cortin or vvall of a Tovvne or fortresse.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore being shevved concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> the perfection that for the fashion of Fortresses is requisite, howe thy oughte to be buylded with a nombre of corners proportioned ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthelesse, with a iust lēgth of the cortin, and a sufficient distaunce betwéene euerye bulwarke, so that the more that with like conditions to the circular fashion it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembleth, so much the more it becommeth perfect.</p>
               <p>There now remained to be cōsidered, what fashiō is to be iudged of moste perfection, either the same whiche without any edification placed in the middest of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin therof, shalbe builded, or that which shal haue either caualiers, or platformes, or what so euer other maner of edification or figure, that for to defende the cortins of the bulwarkes may be placed: or whether it be of those fashiōs, which vnto this present hath bene vsed of other in buylding, or some new maner that might be deuised Therefore in this part leauing to reason of those, that shall haue caualiers or platformes as also of those bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warkes that the cortins shall haue, which from the one to the other moste straightlye without other edification placed in the middest do shoote, for this time I shall only shewe a newe fashion, the which I iudge to be the most perfectest, that is possible to be imagined, as maye bée séene by the lines y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> are drawen from the plaine plat of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> nūber of 3. &amp; by the plat that is raised vp of the nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:176553:19"/> of .4. here vnder figured, which resembling so nere the circular figure, as the due length of the curtin will suffer, they shal haue this difference frō the other which directly are distended, that the cortin being made backe a conueniente distaunce, that spase maye be lefte mete to make from the one and the other poincte of the same retire, a flanker, as twoo like flankers maye be séene, in the plaine platte of the number of .3. by the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>.E.</hi> and <hi>.F.</hi> and in the platte that is raysed vp of the number of .4. by the letters <hi>.A.</hi> and <hi>.C.</hi> they shall haue commoditie to directe their ordinaunce to flancke, as well highe as lowe, like vnto those that are commonly builte nowe a dayes: whereby, not onely the same space of the curtin, that is betwene the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them shalbe perfectlye defended, as maye be perceyued by the platte of the number of .3. by the line drawen from the letter <hi>.E.</hi> to the letter <hi>.F.</hi> but also that whiche lieth betwéen them and the bullwarkes, as in the saide platte, by the lines that describeth the manner of the shotte the one from the letter <hi>.E.</hi> to the letter <hi>.S.</hi> the other from the letter <hi>.F.</hi> to the letter <hi>.R.</hi> maye be vnderstand, and likewyse the curteines of those bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warkes, as also in the verye same, by the line that is drawne from the letter <hi>.F.</hi> to the letter <hi>.Q.</hi> is showed, with a better maner than in other fashion of building that is vsed can be defended, so that all the partes of them shall not onelie be made to be able to shoote by flanke, but also thereby to shoote by righe line, as in the platte of the number of .4. by the line that passeth from the letter <hi>.C.</hi> to the letter <hi>.D.</hi> and from the letter <hi>A.</hi> to the letter <hi>.B.</hi> maye be perceiued. And whereas they maye be builded with lesse coste then otherwise, they haue also commoditie to make their gates equallye distante the one from the other, from the nexte bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warkes: where they are placed moste safelie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouslie with greate strengthe, and those gates be as
<pb facs="tcp:176553:20"/> well, as all the reste of the wall, and greatlier in that parte, much surer from the assailing of the enemies, thē in what so euer other maner of fashion mighte be deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed: for as muche as the platforms, and caualiers bée no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing so strong, but more easie to bée ouerthrowen, in respecte to this maner of building, which is moste sure from such daunger, and excedingly well defended from the force of the enemie: to the which, the nerer that the enemie shall approche, so much the more he shal of those within be hurt, cōtrarie to that, which in the platformes happeneth. Moreouer there maye be certayne slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter houses builte in the diche, as in the plat of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of .4. by the letters <hi>.F.H.</hi> is shewed, which y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> enemies with greate difficultie must firste séeke to winne, before they can come nere the walles. And those being wonne, shall be but small preiudise to the towne or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tresse: wherefore without comparison, this fashion is greatelier to bee praised, then the same with platformes for that the nerer the Walle, the enemie shall come, soo much more from the bulwarkes by flanke, and all most on the backe, and from other places, both by flanke, and by fronte in one instant, he shalbe hurte and stroken.</p>
               <p>Where also in suche a kinde of fashion with many cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, the greatenes and roome of the towne within, is somwhat deminished, in respect to those that are made with platformes. Therefore I conclude, for the consideracions a foresaide, these to bée the moste perfectest fashions that any strong fortresse, is possible to bée made.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:176553:20"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of a fortification</figDesc>
                  <p>5 A B D G K N</p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:176553:21"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of a fortification</figDesc>
                  <p>6. C G B F N M D I K <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </figure>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:176553:21"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of a fortification</figDesc>
                  <p>3. A C E D F F G I H K Z P Q</p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:176553:22"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of a fortification</figDesc>
                  <p>4. D B E G H</p>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:176553:22"/>
               <head>¶ An example of the quadrant forme to prooue that it causeth debilletie and vveakenesse.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE tovvnes &amp; fortresses that</hi> are buylded after a foure cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nered fashion, in what so e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer maner they be made, are subiect to moste great incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences: for that the sharpe corners of their bulwarkes whiche of necessitie the same fashion will cause them to haue, may very easyly be bat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tered, and vnder the ruine therof, the assaultes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies defended, as in the platte following of the nombre of 7. by the bulwarke <hi>C.</hi> battered of the artillerle <hi>D.</hi> is séene. Whereby also maye be perceyued how the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce may be planted to make a breatche, and to take awaye their flanckers after such sort, that the enemies maye safelye approche to anye place, either marching in battelray to incampe, or assaulte, or with pianers to worke, or for any other purpose, as by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> foure flanckers of the thrée bulwarke. <hi>L.E.C.</hi> may be vnderstande, the whiche of the artillerie. <hi>H.F.K.G.</hi> not onely are batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but also twoo of them that haue the letters. <hi>L. C.</hi> as is séene, may of the artillerie. <hi>K. G.</hi> bée beaten through their flanckers, &amp; the backe of the bulwarke. <hi>E.</hi> néerest to them, which is on both sides of the flanckes battered, the which for hauing in such place lesse thickenesse then anye where els, and great heigth, maye bee the more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selier ruinated. as is to bée séene in the sayde bulwarke. <hi>E.</hi> battered with the artillerie <hi>F.</hi> and <hi>H.</hi> and also by the breatche of the batterye, whiche in the cortin is made of the ordinaunce <hi>B.</hi> as is séene where the artillerie <hi>G.</hi> by the cortin doth beate through the same in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> breatch of the batterye <hi>A.</hi> as manifestly appeareth: and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer
<pb facs="tcp:176553:23"/> when they within woulde do any thing, they shall be beaten with the artillerie ouer the wall within the cortin <hi>N.</hi> frō the caualier <hi>M.</hi> without, so that no man shalbe able to stande behinde the same to defende. And not onely in this sorte, but in sundrye wise, and in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse maners, what soeuer towne or fortresse is buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded after such fashion, maye easely be battered &amp; soone made sautable, whereby without further decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration it is playnly to be vnderstande, how much the foresaid plattes of the other fashion ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel this.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:176553:23"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of a square fortification</figDesc>
                     <p>7. Y S A N</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:176553:24"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>Of the nature of Saltpeter, and the</hi> maner hovve to make and refine it.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Altpeter is a mixture of</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye substaunces, gotten out with fire and water of drie &amp; durtie ground, or of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> flower, that groweth oute of newe walles, in Sellars, or of that grounde which is found lose within toombes, or desolate caues, where raine can not come in: in the which grounde (according to my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente) the same is ingendered of an ayrie moistenesse drunke vp, and gotten of the yearthy drines: whose na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (by the effect therof) considering, I cannot tell how to be resolued, to saye what thing properly it is. The well learned and most wise Phisitions (besides medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinall experience) by the taste (finding it salte, and with excéeding sottill sharpenesse, and considering the great byting therof) suppose verylye that it is of nature hotte and drye: on the other parte, séeing it to be a thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendered of ayre, and touched of fyre to fall in a flame, and vapore, and rise with a terrible violence (as the same compounded, is séene by Gonpoulder moste ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestly declared) séemeth to bée of an ayrie nature, hot and moiste: and againe séeing it with shining and glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering whitnesse, as a thing to the nature of water con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable, it séemeth that it maye bée sayde, that it is of a waterye nature, finding it heauye: to whiche maye bée ioyned the experience of the taste, and of the excéeding coldenesse that in somer it causeth the water to bée of, wherein it is put to kéepe Wine colde, as they vse in Italye, and by the brittelnesse therof, it may be thoughte to bée of the nature of earth: and so muche the more, where burning it with as muche brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone, it will tourne into a harde white stone: so that to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:176553:24"/> conclude, it semeth that it hath the soueraintie &amp; quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of euerie elemente. Nowe this of aunciente wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, was called nitro: and Plinie in his naturall histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in the .xxxj. booke sayeth, that it differeth not muche from salte: whose nature semes also that vnto Phisiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons hath not bene hid: &amp; it is found in manie places, but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> best is foūde Macedonia: Albeit the late writers, spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially they of our partes, say that Plinie, and the other writers beleued that it was minerable: &amp; peraduēture they are deceyued: for that there is of the artificial: which hath the very same vertue, &amp; as some thinke, more strō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of nature: &amp; is founde for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> very same medicinall ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, better then the naturall. Nowe this (as I haue sayde) is drawen foorthe from the sayde durtie yearthe, so that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yearthie drines by raine hath not bene extinct: but the moste excellenteste of all other, is made of the dunge of beastes, conuerted into yearth, in stabells or in dunghilles, of long time not vsed: and aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of the same that cōmeth of hogges, the moste and best is gotten: what so euer dunge it be of, it is requisite y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> by continuance of time it be well resolued into yerth, and the humiditie therof dried: yea and it is néedefull y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the same yearthe be as it were dustie. To minde too haue a saye to knowe whether it bée good, by the taste of the tong it maye be felte if it be byting, and howe muche: and finding it strong, so that you determine to woorke of it (making a great quantitie) it is neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie to prouide manie Cauldrons, fornesses, barrills or tubbes: and likewyse wood, white lime, and asshes of olde oke: but chieflie muste be prouided a great barne, or other walled house nere to the water (whereof it is nedefull to haue inoughe, as also of yearthe, both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious for the place, &amp; likewise euery other thing.) But firste the fornesses muste be made for the caul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons, and they muste be placed thereon, as those be
<pb facs="tcp:176553:25"/> that the diers vse: then there must bée prepared ioystes as long as the house, and soo broade, that commodius<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie aboue grounde maie stande buttes with their heads knocked oute, square chestes, barrels or tubbes to the number of .50. or .60. or .100, (according to the caul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, and the capacetie of the place) and betwene euerie twoo of those vessells, there muste be set a halfe tubbe to receiue the water that shall run oute: or there woulde be placed a channell of wood that maye gooe along vnder the holes of the vessells that are set aboue grounde, soo that it maye conuey all the water that commeth from them, into a greate tubbe or twoo suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiente to hold all the water ful of substaunce of Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter: and the buttes that haue their headdes knoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked oute, or barrells or tubbes, in the bottom of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie of them there muste be made a hole on the one syde, with an Awgar, or els thrée or fower littell holes made with a good bigge perser: and vpon them muste be layde a littell thinne linnen clothe or els the ende of a brome, or some strawe, to the intente that it maie kepe the yearthe vp and straine the water that shalbe put amongeste the same yearthe which is to be wrought, when it is tasted with the mouth, so that it be certaine, that it containeth Saltepeter. Then there muste be made thereof, in the middest of the house where it is to be wroughte, a greate hill, nexte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which muste be made an other halfe so bigge, which must be made with twoo pares of vnslaked lime, and thrée of oke asshes, or other asshes, which in taste are verie strong and sharpe: and then the one hill muste be well mingled with the other, and with the same com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, the tubbes muste be filled that are set a lofte vpon the ioystes, within a span of the mowthe, or else (minding not to mingell with the yearth the asshes &amp; the lime together) you maie put firste a spanne thicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:176553:25"/> of yearth in the bottome of the tubbe, and then thrée fingers thicknes of the forsayde lime and asshes: and vpon the same after, an other spanne thicknes of yearthe, and on that likewyse, an other thrée or fowre fingers thicknes of lime and asshes: and so putting one rewe of one thing, and an other of an other, you shall fill all the buttes and tubbes, or other vessells that you haue placed, euen as aboue I haue sayde, wythin a spanne of the mouthes of them, and the reste that is then emptie, which you lefte, you muste fill with water: the which running throughe all the yearthe, by a littell and a littell, you muste let it droppe in the tubbes that stande vnder to receyue it, or in the gutter or channell, or where you liste, so that it be conueyed into one or into sundrie tubbes, or where you thincke good: and so you muste sée well that you gather all the water that you powred vppon the yearthe, after it is passed throughe the holes of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the tubbes, in suche wyse, that it bring with it all the substaunce and vertue of the Saltepeter that was in the sayde yearth: whereof by putting some of it on your tongue, you maye taste: and finding it biting and very salte, it is a token that it is good and that you haue done well: if not, powre it agayne vpon the verye same yearthe, or vpon some other newe: but fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the firste yearthe full of substaunce as muche as sufficeth, you maye agayne powre vpon it more water, too wasshe better the remnaunte of the yearth: albeit this seconde water woulde be saued in an other vessell, and after this, the yearth maye likewise be wasshed the thirde time, to thintente that all the substaunce there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, maye perfectlie be gotten: but this seconde nor the thirde, ought not to be mingled with the firste, if it happen not to come of the verie same taste: the whiche I beleue that it will not: but it must be put by it selfe in other vessells, for that it is good to powre vpon the
<pb facs="tcp:176553:26"/> chaunge of the nexte yearth, and so you maye procede, gathering a good quantitie of suche water, taking héede neuerthelesse, that it be full of the substaunce of Salte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter: the whiche if it séeme vnto you, not of the same perfection, as you woulde haue it, you maye powre it againe vpon the verie same yearth, or vpon other new, till suche time as it satisfie you, and that you knowe, that it be full of the substaunce of Saltepeter. Besides this, there muste be made a furnes with one or .ij. caul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons of brasse walled thereon, whiche muste be as greate as those that the Diers vse, and these cauldrons muste then be filled, with the foresaide Saltepeter wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: the whiche (as alredie I haue tolde) oughte to be as full of substaunce as maie be, so that it haue aboute the .ij. third partes, and make it faire and softlie to boile so much till it come to one thirde part, or there aboutes: and after take it of, and put it to settell in a greate ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell, couered, whiche muste be well bounde aboute, with hoopes of yron, and sure and close in the ioyning thereof, to the intente it spill not: and thus when the same water is setled and well clarefied, and from the yearthe and grose matter, whiche in it remained, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently purged, it muste be taken oute and boyled againe of newe in the same cauldron, or in some other: and for as muche as euerye time that it boileth, if it be not taken héede of, it turneth into skum, and sometimes swelleth so muche, that often times running ouer it spilleth, and carrieth awaye therewith muche of the good: the whiche minding to reméedie, you muste take thrée partes of Oke asshes, and one of lime, and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, in euerie hundrethe pounde waighte of water, there muste be dissolued fower pounde of roche Alum: and when the cauldron boileth, take of the sayde wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with a pot, and powre into it ones or twise, and spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially when you sée the Saltepeter water rise in skum, whiche in a little while you shall sée it alaie, bothe clere
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:176553:26"/> and faire, and of an azur colour: and it muste bée boyled so long, till all the thinne watrinesse bée vapored away and the substaunce of the Saltpeter thickened: so that it being taken out, and put in chestes or tubbes and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, maye congeale: the whiche is best done, when the water is brought to least quantitie, taking it out and putting it into a lesse caudron, wherein it will sooner congeale: the whiche water being tasted, and séene to bée brought to suche passe, to bée reade to congeale, you maye take it out, and put it in vesselles of wood, or of earth that are rough within, with certayne stickes of wood, to congeale, and so you shall let it coole, and rest. iij. or iiij. daies, so as it maye drop, and be strayned through some litle hole, in the bottom of the vessell: and all the water that is not then congealed, you must take out and saue for to séeth againe: and the Saltpeter that is in anye quantitie congealed, you shall finde to bée, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the vertue that was in the water, or in the earth: but the clerenesse and fairnesse thereof, will come of the maister vertue of the water, that is put into it in the boyling, which hath strength to purgeit, and make it come, as it were refined in the first séething: nowe this being taken from the sides of the vessell, where it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gealed, and in the water therof washed, you must laye it vpon a table to drie throughlye: and the same séeming vnto you to haue néede, or neuerthelesse minding to haue it aboue the common vse, for some purpose, more purefied, &amp; without earthy grosnesse, &amp; altogether with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fatnesse and saltnesse, whiche for to make excéeding fine pouder, or <hi>aqua fortis,</hi> is most requisit so to be: to be short, for what so euer cause it oughte to be refined, I councell you, to do it after one of these ij. wayes, whiche here following, I shall teach you. The first, which I like best, is with water: and the seconde is with fire, with water it is refined in this maner, taking of the foresaid mixture made of lime, asshes, and allome dissolued: and
<pb facs="tcp:176553:27"/> then for euerie barrell of water that you haue put in the cauldron, for to disolue the Saltepeter, you muste put into it sixe pottefulls of the foresayd strong water: and in the same quantitie of water so prepared, put so muche Saltpeter as you thinke maye well be dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: and with boyling make it to resolue verye well, and séeing it in boyling too haue caste vp scum, you shall then take it oute of the cauldron, and put it into a tubbe, in the bottome where of, you muste firste haue put fower fingers thicknes of fine sande cleane washed, and that muste be couered with a linnen clothe: and by a littell hoole made in the bottome of the tubbe, you shall suffer it to droppe by littell and littell into some other vessell set vnder to receiue it: &amp; so this water thus strai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, you must after put in the verie same or in an other cauldron to boile agayne, and to make the greater parte of the same water, that you put into it séethe awaye: fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally make it boyle so muche, vntill you sée it readie to thicken, powering nowe and than, in making it, a littell of the foresayde strong water, and speciallye when it swelleth and casteth vp scum: and this thing (being soo handled) you muste take it oute of the cawl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, and put it in chestes or other vessells of wood, to congeale: whiche, being a greate quantitie, in thrée or fower dayes, you shall finde all that congealed, which will congeale: which, being taken oute, you muste or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as you vsed afore the other: and the same water that is not congealed, muste be boyled agayne: and so you shall doo from time to time as it gathereth together and congealeth: and after this sorte you shall make the Saltepeter moste white and faire, and much better thē at the firste séething.</p>
            <p>Also saltepeter is refined in an other manner, whiche is with fire, but in a littell quantitie mynding to doo it well: and although it be a readie waye, yet fewe vse it: albeit it serueth to get oute the fatnes of saltepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:176553:27"/> for that it sendethe into the bottome verye muche yearthynes, notwithstanding I like better the foresaide waye in purging it with water, then this with fire:</p>
            <p>But to doo this, take a salet, or some other yron or brasen vessell, and fill it with Saltpeter, and couer it with a couer of yron, brasse or yearth, soo that it be made bigge inoughe, méete to bée taken of and put on when you liste, that the vessell maye be well couered: and then it muste bée set in the middest of a good fire of cooles, and so the Saltepeter will melte, whiche is soone perceyued of the experte artificer: but when you thinke that it is molte, looke vpon it: and if it be not well mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, couer it agayne and let it melte well: then it béeing well molten, take brimstone mooste finelye beaten in powlder, and strawe some thereon: and if of it selfe it take not fire, doo you kindell it: and being kindeled let it burne till suche time as the brimstone be all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed, so that nothing ells be burnte, but the vpper parte, and certayne grosse vnctiousnes of the Saltepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the whiche when it is burned, will leaue the reste faire and cleare: and then it muste bée taken from the fire letting it coole, where in the vesseell you shall find it (when it shalbe coulde) all in one péece white like vnto a péece of marbell: and all the yearthinesse thereof remayning in the bottome: whiche shalbe good saltepeter to make powlder withall, but not verie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable to anie other vse: and aboute saltepeter the witte of men haue so muche imagened, that meanes are founde to cause it to growe in the grounde, and in places: that neuer had anie before, by disoluing Salte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter in water: for with the same water wetting the grounde, and letting it stande so a certayne space of time, saltepeter wil be ingendred, so that the same that was put there, will multiplie wonderfully: and it is a moste certayne thing, that in making Saltepeter, the yearthe that hathe béene occupied, heaped vp in a
<pb facs="tcp:176553:28"/> place that is couered, so that the rayne do not washe it, within the space of fiue or sixe yeres, maye agayne bée laboured, and Saltpeter shalbe founde to be ingendred, and yéelde much more, then it dyd the first time: &amp; this that I haue declared in this chapter, is as much as I can saye of Saltpeter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The maner hovve to make all sortes of Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouder. Chapter xxiiii.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Vnpouder, is made of three</hi> simples onely: that is, saltpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Brimstone and Coales: and some proportioneth it after one fashion, and some after an other, and also accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Gunnes, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses, wherewith they will occupye it. For that one sorte is occupied for great ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, and an other sorte for lesse péeces: and this is knowen to euerye Bombardier: In Harkabuses, and hande gunnes, is not occupied common pouder, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute certayne fire woorkes: and therefore to euerye of the sayde purposes, the pouders is proporcioned ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly For that if Serpentine pouder, should be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in hande gunnes, or Harkebuses, it woulde scāt be able to driue their pellettes a quaites caste frō their mouthes: and if hande gunne pouder shoulde bée vsed in péeces of ordinaunce, without great discretion, it woulde quickely breake or marre them: and to minde to haue all sorte of pouders good, thrée thinges is requisit to bée obserued, in making therof. The first is to sée, that the substaunce, wherewith it is made, haue no earthie grossenesse. The seconde, that it be finely bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: the thirde, that it bée verye well dried, from all
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:176553:28"/> humiditie or moistenesse, and this doone, you shall haue strong and excellent good pouder. And it is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standed, that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> chiefe thing that is in pouder, is Saltpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: for that of it (by the same that is séene) dependeth all the forse. And therefore prouision is to be made, to haue a good quantitie thereof, and that it be cleane and nete: the which by burning, maie well be knowen, for that in all sortes of pouder, it is néedefull, that the Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter be good.</p>
            <p>Now, for to make common pouder, for greate péeces of artillerie there must be taken thrée partes, of refined Saltpeter, twoo of Willowe cooles, &amp; one of Brimstone, and grinding euery thing: all muste be well mingled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, &amp; all the moistnesse thereof dried vp, as I haue saide. To make pouder for small péeces of artillerye, there muste be taken fiue partes, of refined Saltpeter, and one and a halfe of Cooles, and one of Brimstone, &amp; grinding it moste finelie, and mingling it well together, it muste be corned, and then dried. The maner of corning all sortes of pouder, is with a Séeue made, with a thicke skinne of Parchemēt, full of little round holes, into the whiche Séeue the pouder muste be put, while it is dancke, and also a little bowle, that when you sifte, it maie roule vp and doune, vpon the clottes of pouder, to breake them, that it maie corne, and runne throughe the hooles of the Séeue.</p>
            <p>To make Harkebuse and hande Gunne pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, there muste be taken tenne partes of refined salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter, and one of young hasell cooles of a yeare olde made cleane, and one parte of Brimstone, and beating all in a mortar, or grinding it excedingly well that it maye be mingled together and so fine as is possible, thē it muste be corned and throughlie dried. And note that if it be not marueylously well beaten, it wil neuer be good. But because making of pouder, whiche are of thinges that will easylie kindell, cannot be withoute
<pb facs="tcp:176553:29"/> perrill of him that maketh it, excepte it bée remedied with wetting: therefore it behoueth to take héede that it be not beaten drie, as well to auoyde suche perrill, as also for that it will be beaten better: for whiche cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses it muste be wet with comun water to a certaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée of moistenes, so that taken vp in ones hande it maye cling together. Some moiste it with vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: and some, for to make it more stronger, with cāp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hored, <hi>aqua vitae.</hi> When I haue caused gunpouder to bée made, I haue vsed comun water, &amp; therefore I am able to saye whiche of those thinges is beste: and to tell my opinion, I doubt whether vineger or, <hi>aqua vitae,</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the gunpoulder to be any better then the comun water: for as much they vaporyng awaye, as they doo, &amp; as of necessitie they must, I beléeue that littell of their substance remayneth.</p>
            <p>There bée some whiche in making coole (béesides wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low) make thē of hasell: &amp; some of vyne stickes: &amp; some of baye stickes: some of réedes: some of kexses: &amp; to bée shorte, all the cooles that are made of softe wood, are of wood which haue much pith: but it is requisit that they be smalle, yong, and tender, and withoute hardenes of knottes: otherwyse they be not good.</p>
            <p>Albeit they be made in diuers maners: but in making of any great quantitie of pouder, the ordinarie coole is to be taken: and makyng a littell, they vse to take yong hasell of a yeare olde, cut in shorte péeces, and they putting them into a greate yearthen potte,<note place="margin">Hovve too make coole vvhere vvith gunpoulder is made.</note> or other vessell of yron, or brasse, they shutte it and couer it close, and lute it, or daube it very well aboute, so that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not breathe: and then they make fire rounde aboute it and vpon it, till suche time as it maye bée thoughte that the heate is well entred in through all, and that the wood that is within is very well fired: and without fire-brandes, or flame, burned onely through suche heate: and then they take the fire from the potte and let it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:176553:29"/> coole, and so they finde the same wood become cole. I hapning once to haue néede of coles (to thintent to make some quicklie,) toke as manie drie hasel stickes that had their rindes scrapes of, as I thought sufficiente to serue my purpose: and breaking them in péeces and laying them close together on a heape, I set them on fire and burned them all well, and then sprinckeled water vpon them with a browne, and with the same wet browme quenched the fire: and so scattered abrode y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> coles héere &amp; there, alwayes sprinckling water vpon thē till I quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched them: and thus I haue serued my purpose withoute so muche difficultie.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, it is a verie profitable thing, yea and a necessarie, that I declare the maner and facilitie of beating it, for to be able safelie to make a greate quantetie thereof. In olde time they were wonte to grinde gunpouder with certayne handemilles, as they vse to grinde corne, but (besides the paine) it is a waye verie perrillous: for that suche a composition grounde together with stones, will catche heate in suche wyse, that it will soone ingender fire, inespecially euery thing being a matter disposed to fire: as also by rubbing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with violence a couple of baye stickes, you shall straighte waye kendel fire. Some grinde pouder in suche milles as they vse to grinde crabbes or apples to make vargis or sider: and some hath it stamped in mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with a water mille or a horsemill, whiche waye is the beste of all other, and moste surest and also it is beaten finelier, and with lesse labour and payne: Some (that hath not the commodetie of water) make a greate whéele, deuised after such sorte, that with the cogges thereof it may raise vp many heauy pestels, which fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, beate in diuers morters of woodde made in a beame of oke, of the whiche there be some haue the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes of brasse.</p>
            <p>Some stampe with their armes, with a greate pestel
<pb facs="tcp:176553:30"/> tied to the ende of a pole with a corde, righte euer a morter of wood or brasse, and so they bease the ease<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier: other some beate it in a stone morter, with the mouthe some what large, with a wooden pestell, with the handell thereof made like vnto a hammer or a mall. And these, and other, that maye be made, is as much as aboute the deeuise of bealing and making gun pouder is néedefull.</p>
            <p>They haue vsed heretofore to waighe euery mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by it selfe, and then they haue gone mingling and beating all together: There haue béene after, some that haue deuised to beate euery thing seuerallye by it selfe, and then mingelled altogether and made it. But finally the beste and moste readiesse waye, is to take a quantetie of Saltepeter, wherewith you will make youre poulder, and put it into a catildron with so much water (as being set vpon the fire) maye be thought sufficiente to dissoule it: whiche so sone as it is resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, muste be taken of and set on the grounde in a colde place: and the quantetie of beaten coles that is suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciente, muste be put into it, and so sturring it aboute, muste be mingled well with the Saltpeter dissolued: and then taking youre brimstone finely beaten in pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and with a staffe stirring aboute the coles and the Saltepeter, you muste strawe it finely vpon the same, as well as you can, with continuall sturring and mingling them together, whiche composition thus made, you muste then drie somewhat in the sunne: and then to haue it excellently well made, there néedeth no other to be done, but to beate it alltogether, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente that it maye incorporate moste finely, whiche done, you muste drie it with moste greate diligence: and then si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t it very well through a sieue, and moisting it againe with water or vineger, sturring it somewhat together in a sieue, you maye corne it as alreadie hath bene declared: and then againe for to occupye it aboute
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:176553:30"/> your businesse your muste daye it well: and so being dried put it into daye vessels of wood to kéepe: and set it in the highest places of your house, where few commeth for diuers respectes: and though it were for no other, at least to kéepe it drie. They tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are expert, knowe good pouder in this maner, by the colour: for that if it be very blacke it is a signe y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it is made with very muche coles: or that it is moyste: and when you rubbe it vppon a peece of paper it will blacke it more then it ought to doo: and drawing it with your finger, you maye sée whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bée finely beaten or no: for it muste bée so much beaten that nothing, neither of Saltepeter nor of Brimstone bee diserned in anye, wise: for with reason they oughte not to bée seene: they take also for a triall, thrée or foure cornes of pouder, and laye them vpon a white Paper, distaunte thrée fingers, the one from the other, and fire one of them: and if the pouder bée good, you shall sée them all to fire at ones: so that there shall bée no residence remayning, neither grossenesse of Brimstone, nor of Saltpeter, nor of any other thing, and the paper not burnte.</p>
            <p>And if it be not so founde, then knowe that it is euyll made, or not good, but full of earth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nesse of Saltepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: or that it is moyst, so that it is naught for shooting of ordinaunce, besides the perill that it putteth them in. And vndoubtedl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e naughtye pouder, is a cost halfe caste awaye: and it is a great faulte in him that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it, or that causeth it to bée made: for that in time of néede, it is of no effecte, and causeth muche shame to the Gunners, which occupie it: and therefore dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence oughte to bée vsed, and good héede taken that it be made according as I haue taughte. There are manye whiche bring vp lies, saying: that they can tell howe to make pouder that shoting it in gunnes shall make no noise, the whiche is impossible, the fire and the ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e violentlye incountering together, where besides th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t
<pb facs="tcp:176553:31"/> they are not able to do the same they saye, with a péece of ordinance, they are lesse able to do it with one of those potgunnes of elder, that boyes vse to shut paper and slowes in, by the noise of which, maye well be percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that all proceadeth of breaking of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ayre. Also there be manye that saye, that they can make white pouder, that shall not blacke ones handes, by putting in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thing in the stéede of cooles: some other, redde, with dried red flowres: and other blewe, with blew flowers: some other saye that to make the pouder of more force and strength, that it is very good to put to euery pounde of brimstone an ounce of mercurie, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> brimstone being first put in by a litle, and a litle. Moreouer there are some other that saye, that for to make the like, there ought to be put to euery pound of Saltpeter, a quarter of an ounce of Salt armoniack: some other therebe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, whiche saye that in the stéede of coales, it is better to take linen cloth and to burne it to tinder, and therwith to make pouder, whiche is more excellenter then anye other coale that is possible to be vsed, about suche a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. And although that in my iudgement I haue decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red alréedy the best receites, that is for the making of all sortes of gunpouder, yet to the intent that it may be vnderstande howe much men haue trauayled and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gened to bring the same to all perfectiō, I haue thought good to showe herefollowing diuers moe receiptes both good and bad, which for the making of pouder hath béene experiensed of sundrie men.</p>
            <div type="powder_recipes">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:176553:31"/>
               <list>
                  <head>The first inuention and oldest maner <hi>in making of sarpentine pouder, or pouder</hi> for ordinaunce.</head>
                  <item>1 Saltepeter i. parte.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone i. parte</item>
                  <item>Coles i. parte.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>The nexte practis of making pouder for ordinaunce.</head>
                  <item>2. Saltepter iij. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone ii. partes.</item>
                  <item>Coles ii. partes.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>¶ Pouder for ordinaunce of a newer making.</head>
                  <item>3. Saltepeter x. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone iij. partes.</item>
                  <item>Coles iij. partes.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>¶ Pouder for ordinaunce not so olde.</head>
                  <item>4. Saltpeter xij. partes</item>
                  <item>Brimstone iij. partes.</item>
                  <item>Coles. ii. partes.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Pouder for ordinaunce not verie olde.</head>
                  <item>5. Saltpeter ix. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone ij. partes.</item>
                  <item>Coles iij. partes.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Pouder vsed of late daies for handgunnes.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176553:32"/>
                  <item>6. Saltpeter iiii. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone i. parte</item>
                  <item>Coles i. parte.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Pouder for ordinaunce vsed not so long ago<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</head>
                  <item>7. Saltepeter xx. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone iii. partes.</item>
                  <item>Coles x. partes.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>¶ Pouder for ordinaunce vsed of latter daies.</head>
                  <item>8. Saltepeter x. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone x. partes.</item>
                  <item>Coles xxxvj. partes.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>¶ Grossepouder of a newer sorte.</head>
                  <item>9. Saltpeter x. partes</item>
                  <item>Brimstone xx. partes.</item>
                  <item>Colds. xxxvii. partes.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>¶ Fine pouder of a making not very olde.</head>
                  <item>10. Saltpeter ix. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone iij. partes.</item>
                  <item>Coles v. partes.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>¶ Grosse pouder of a newer making.</head>
                  <item>11. Saltepeter ij. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone i. parte.</item>
                  <item>Coles. i. parte.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:176553:32"/>
                  <head>Harkabus pouder of <hi>a newer making.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>12. Saltpeter iij. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone. i. parte.</item>
                  <item>Coles of willowe stickes i. parte.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>
                     <hi>¶</hi> Fine pouder of a newer making.</head>
                  <item>13. Saltpeter often refined v. partes</item>
                  <item>Brimstone i. parte.</item>
                  <item>Coles of young hasell stickes i. parte.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>¶ Grosse pouder of a nevver making.</head>
                  <item>14. Saltpeter refined iij. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone i. parte.</item>
                  <item>Willowe coles ii. partes</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Pouder of a nevver making.</head>
                  <item>15. Saltpeter x. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone ii. partes.</item>
                  <item>Willow coles iii. partes.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>¶ Harkabus pouder vsed novve adayes.</head>
                  <item>16. Saltpeter very often <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>fined x. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone i. parte.</item>
                  <item>Coles made of Hasell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>gges with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> like pilled i. parte.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Hand gun pouder of a nevver making</head>
                  <item>17. Saltpeter refined xvi. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone iii. partes</item>
                  <item>Coles of hasell hauing their rindes pilled of .iiij. partes.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176553:33"/>
                  <head>¶ Handgun pouder of a stronger and of a newer making.</head>
                  <item>18. Saltpeter refined vij. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone. i. parte.</item>
                  <item>Coles of young hasell i. parte.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>¶ Finer and stronger handegun pouder.</head>
                  <item>19. Saltpeter diuers times refined viij. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone i. parte.</item>
                  <item>Coles of young hasell twigges hauing their rindes pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of i. part.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>¶ Grosse pouder vsed novve a daies.</head>
                  <item>20. Saltpeter iiij. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone i. parte.</item>
                  <item>Willowe coles i. parte.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>¶ Grosse pouder vsed novve adayes.</head>
                  <item>21. Saltpeter xx. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone iiii. partes.</item>
                  <item>Willow coles v. partes.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>¶ Handegun pouder vsed novve a daies.</head>
                  <item>22. Saltpeter refined drie xlviii. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone cetrine vii. partes</item>
                  <item>Hasell coles ii. partes.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Handegun pouder vsed novve adaies.</head>
                  <item>23. Saltpeter refined xviii. partes.</item>
                  <item>Brimstone ii. partes.</item>
                  <item>Hasel coles iii. partes.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:176553:33"/>
               <head>¶ The maner that is vsed of charging and shooting of ordinaunce. Cap. xxv.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or asmuche as if Gunners</hi> should chaunce to bée slaine or otherwise lacking, to the intent that euery souldiour in time time of néede maye knowe how to serue in one of their stéedes, I haue thought good and necessarye to shew and declare the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of charging &amp; shooting of péeces of ordinaunce. Wherfore it ought to bée vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstoode, howe muche pouder is occupied at once in charching of euery péese, whiche moste commonly, is is twoo thirde partes, of that which the shotte or bullet thereof wayeth: as for example if the boolet of a péese of ordinaunce waighe .xxi. pounde, then there must bée taken .xiiii. pounde of pouder for the iuste charge of the same péese. And then with a long staffe that hath at the one ende a bob as big as the boolet of the péese, and at the other ende a ladle made for the same purpose that will take so muche pouder vp at twise or thrise, as is aforesayd, the péese must be charged, after this fort. Take the ladle full of pouder, and thrust it into the Gunne so farre as it will go, &amp; then turne your hande with the ladle that the pouder maye fall out &amp; remaine there behinde when you pull out your ladle: whiche done, you muste with the bob ende thereof, thrust the pouder home faire and softelye: and so with the ladle taking vp the rest of the pouder you must doo likewise, and thrust after at the last a wispe of hey or of some thing els, to swepe all the poulder together, and then the bullet whiche muste bée of a fit biggnesse for the péese: And also an other wispe to staye the bollet for roling oute: and putting some pouder in the touchehole and aboute the touchchole, the Gunne is then charged.
<pb facs="tcp:176553:34"/> Nowe to leuell it, a man must stande directly behinde it, and with a leuer, tourne it this waye, or that waye till suche time as it be broughte to lie iuste, as a man will haue it, so that looking straighte from the breache or hinder parte of the péece as lowe as maye bée vpon the vpper parte thereof, he maye sée the mouth of the péece to lye euen with the marke and as it were to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it: whiche done, if the grounde wheron it standeth, bée euen, as it is requisite to bée, and that the one whele stande not higher then the other, giuing fire to it with a linte stocke whiche is a matche fastened to the end of a staffe of a yarde or twoo yardes long, you shall sée the shot to strike the same thing that you shot at, if it bée within anye reasonable distance. And for more spéedie shoting of ordinaunce, the iuste charge in pouder of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye péece may aforhāde be prepared in a readinesse, and put in bagges of linnen or in great papers made for the same purpose, which in a sodaine may be chopt into the mouth of a péece with the boollet or shot there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of thrust after, as farre as they will go, and then thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting a long wyer into the touchehole that maye perse through the bagge or paper wherin the charge of pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der lieth within the péece, filling the same touchehole with corne pouder so soone as it is leueled, it maye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continent be shot of: whiche maner of charging is done most quickely and a great deale sooner then any other waye, and when haste requires, very néedefull.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:176553:34"/>
               <head>¶ How to get out quickely the nailes that should hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen by treason, or otherwise to be driuen into the toucheholes of ordinaunce. Cap. xxvi.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F it shoulde fortune at some</hi> sodaine assault, the touche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holes of the artillerie to be nayled vp, after suche sorte as they cannot be dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, or shot of, the speediest waye to vnnaile them, is firste to charge againe all suche péeces of artillerie, with smaller bulletes thē their ordinarye: and when they are so charged, to leuel them towarde those places where néede requires, euē as they shoulde haue béene, if they had not béene nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: and then there must bée made a traine of pouder, along the bottome of the canes, from the mouthes to the bollettes of euerye péece of ordinaunce: and to the intente not to shoote them in vaine, you maye tarrye for occasion, and occasion seruing to shoote them, you maye giue fire at their mouthes, where besides that they shall doo their ordinarie effectes, they shall all in the discharging, bée vnayled, blowing oute the same nailes or pinnes of yron, wherewith their toucheholes were stopped: and so doing, of suche nailing there shall happen no great harme. But if some of them for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beating in harder then other, shoulde chaunce at the first not to be driuen out, then the reméedye is, to charge them againe, &amp; to shoote them of, after the saide maner, putting on the toucheholes a litle oyle made very hot, heating also first the place that is nailed, with a burning coale, making moreouer with claye, vpon the péece, a litle cuppe aboute the hole, that maye holde the hot oile that is poured vpon it, after suche
<pb facs="tcp:176553:35"/> sorte, that through the heate thereof, it maye soke into the hole with the yron in it, whereby the same yron shall then be made so slippery, that at the next dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the péese, the fury of the fire most easyly shall blow it oute.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ How much the artillerie ought to be esteemed of the armies novv a daies, and whether the same opinion of them whiche is had vniuersally, be trevve, Cap. xxvij.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsidering howe many</hi> bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes and déedes of armes, were made of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Romanes at sundrie times, there is come vnto mée in conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the vniuersall opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of manye men, which is, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> if in those times there had béene ordinaunce, the Romaines should not haue bene able to haue conquered, nor so easyly haue won the coūtries, and made the people their tributaries, as they dyd, nor they should not haue in any maner made so mightie conquestes. They saye also, that by meane of this instrument of fire, men cannot vse, nor shewe their strength and vertue, as they might in olde time. And they adde a third thing, that they come with more difficultie to fight a field then they came in those daies, nor their cannot be kéepte in them the orders of those times, so that at length the warre shalbe broughte to consiste altogether in artillerie. And minding to write, whether such opinion be true, and howe much the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillerie hath increased, or deminished the strength of armies, and whether it taketh awaye, or giueth occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to good Capitaynes to do valiauntlye, I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:176553:35"/> to speake concerning their firste opinion, that the auncient Romaine armies shoulde not haue made the conquestes whiche they did, if the ordinaunce had béene in those dayes. To which answering I say, how that warre is made eyther to defende, or to offende.</p>
               <p>Where first it is to be examenid, to whom these twoo maner of warres causeth moste profite, or most hurte. And albeit there is what to say of either part, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing I beleue, that withoute comparison, they doo more harme to him that defendeth, thē to him that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uadeth. The reason is, that he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> defendeth, is either in a toune, or in a campe within a trenche. If he be within a toune, this toune is eyther littell, as the moste parte of fortresses are, or it is greate. In the first case, he that defendeth, is altogether loste: for that the violence of the artillerie is suche, that there is no wall, how greate so euer it be, which in few dayes it battereth not doun. And if he that is within, haue not space inoughe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, bothe with diches, and with rampiers, he is ouer come, because he is not abel to withstand the violence of the enemye, whoo throughe the breache of the wall, will after enter: nor in this case, the artillerye whiche he shoulde haue, shall not helpe him: for that this is a generall rule, that where men in a throng, &amp; with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lēnce may go, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> artillerie cannot withold them. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the defence of a toune, the furie of the enemies cannot be withstand. Though the assaultes the which are not thronged, but scattered, which be called scir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mushes be easelye withstode. And they whiche goo with this disorder, and coldenesse to a breache of a walle, where artillerye is, doo goo to a manifeste deathe, and agaynste them the artillerye preuailethe: but those, which assaulte a breache in a throng harde together, so that the one thrusteth forwarde the other if they be not holden oute of diches, or of rampiers, they enter in euerye place, and the artillerye kéepeth
<pb facs="tcp:176553:36"/> them not backe, and though some be slaine, they cānot be so many, that they shall not let the victory. This is knowen to be trew, by many expugnacions of tounes made in Italy, and in especiallie in the same of Bris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia: for as much as the same Towne being rebelled from the frenchemen, and yet the fortresse béeing kept for the King of Fraunce, the Venetians for the with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande the violence, which from the same might come into the toune, had laid all the stréete full of Artillerie, which descended from the fortresse to the Citie, &amp; they planted them on the fronte, and in the flanckes, and in euery other fit place. Of the which Mounsier de Fois made no other coūpte, but with his squadrons, cōming downe on foote passing through the middest of them, gotte the citie: nor it was not knowen that he receiued by those any notable hurte. So that he that defendeth him selfe within a littell Toune (as hath béene sayde) and findeth the walle on the grounde, and hathe not space to retire with rampiers, and with ditches, and is constrayned to truste vpon the artillerye, is ouercome straight way. If thou defendest a great toune, &amp; where thou haste commoditie to retire, yet notwithstanding withoute comparison, the artillerie is more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to him which is withoute, then to him that is within. Firste, to minde to haue a péece of Artillerie hurte those without, thou art constrained to gette thée vp with it from the playne grounde of the Toune, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause standing vpon the plaine grounde, euery littell bancke and rampier that the enemy maie make, shall cause him to remaine safe, and thou canste not hurts him, so that being driuen to stande a loofte on the toppe of the walle, or in what so euer other maner on highe, thou drawest after thée twoo difficulties. The firste is, that thou canste not bring vp so greate and mightye péeses of artillerie, as he withoute may shoote, being not able in littell spaces to handell great thinges. The
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:176553:36"/> other is, that although thou couldest bring them, thou canst not make such strong &amp; sure defence for to saue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said artillerie from dismounting, as they without may doo, being on the groūd, and hauing that commoditie &amp; that roome, that they them selues liste. So that it is im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>possible for him that defendeth a toune, to kéepe the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillerie on high places, when they which are withoute haue greate ordinaunce inough. And if they be driuen to come with thē on lowe places, they become for the moste parte vprofitable, as hath bene sayde. So that the defence of the citie, is brought to be defended with armes, as in olde time they did, and with small artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie. Of which if there be gotten a littell profite (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing respecte to the same small artillerie) there is got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten so much incommoditie, as counterpeaseth the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie of the artillerie: for as much as hauing res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecte to the same, they make the walles of tounes low, and as it were vnder ground in diches, so that so soone as they come to the battaile at hande, eyther because the walles are battered, or because the ditches are fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp, he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is within, hath much more disaduantage, then he shoulde haue had in times paste. And therefore (as afore is sayde) these instrumentes helpeth much more him that besiegeth a towne, then he that is besie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. Concerning the thirde thing, to lye in Campe within a trenche, to the intente not to fighte the fielde but at thy commoditie, or aduauntage, I saye, that in this parte thou hast no more remedy ordinarelie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende thée from fighting, then they had in olde time.</p>
               <p>And sometimes, considering the artillerie, thou haste greater disaduauntage: for that if the enemie méete with thée, and haue a littell aduauntage of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, as may easely chaunce, and finde him selfe higher then thou, or that in his coming thou hast not yet made thy banckes or rampiers, and couered thée well with those, straight waye, and before thou haste anie reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,
<pb facs="tcp:176553:37"/> he vnlodgeth thée, and thou arte constrayned to issue oute of thy fortresse, &amp; come to fighte: the whiche happened to the Spaniardes in the battaile of Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenna, whoo being fortefied betwen the riuer of Ron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, and a bancke, because they lay, not so highe as suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed, and for that the Frenchemen had a littell the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntage of the grounde, they were constrained of the artillerye to issue oute of their Fortresse, and come to fight. But admit that the place, which thou haste taken with the campe, were muche higher, then the other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainste it (as for the most part it ought to be) and that the banckes or rampiers were good and sure, so that by meanes of the situacion, and thy other preparacions the enemie durst not assaulte thée, it shall come in this case to those maners, which in olde time it came, whē one was with his army in place not possible to be hurt: the which are to ouer run the countrie, to take, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siege the tounes that are thy friendes, to stoppe thée thy victualls, so that thou shalte be constrained of some necessetie to vnlodge, and come to fight the field, where the artillerie (as hereafter shalbe sayde) dooth not muche hurte. Considering then what kinde of warres y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Romaines made, and seing how they made almoste all theyr warre to inuade other men, and not for to defende them selues, it shalbe séene (when the thinges sayde afore be trew) how they should haue had more aduauntage, and muche sooner should haue made their conquestes, if ordinaunce had béen in those daies. Concerning the seconde thing, that men cannot shew their strength, as they mighte in olde time, because of the artillerye, I saye, that it is trewe, that where men scattered doo shewe it, they stande in more perrill, then in those dayes, when they had to skale a Towne, or to make like assaultes, where men not thronged to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, but seuerally the one frō the other did apeare.</p>
               <p>It is also trewe that the Capitaines, and headdes of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:176553:37"/> armies, stande more subiecte to the perrill of death: then in those times, because they may be reached with artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie in all places, nor it helpeth not them to bée in the rerewardes, garded with moste strong men. Not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing it is séene, that the one and the other of these twoo perrills, doo seldome times extraordinarie hurtes, for that the Tounes well appoincted and furnished with munition are not scaled, nor they goo not with weake assaultes to assaulte them: but minding to winne them, the matter is broughte to a siege, as in olde time they did. And in those, which neuerthelesse are won by as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salte, the perrills are not much greater then they were in those daies: for that also in those times, they which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended a toune, lacked not thinges to throwe and shoote, the which (though they were not so furius) they did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the kylling of men the like effecte. Concerning the death of Capitaynes and conducters, there hath béen in .xxiiij. yeares that the warre was of late dayes in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly, lesse examples, then there was in .x. yeares with the antiquetie: for that excepte Counte Lodouike of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randola, who died at Ferare, whē the Venecians, a few yeares agon, assalted the same state, and the Duke of Nemors, which died a Cirignuola, there hath not hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the artillery any to be slaine: for as much as Moū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sier de Fois at Rauenna, died of yron, and not of fire.</p>
               <p>So that if men shew not perticularly their strengthes, it groweth not of the artillerie, but of the naughtie orders, &amp; of the weakenes of the armies, the which altogether lacking strength, cannot show it in parte. Cocerning the third thing sayde of them, that men cannot come to hande strokes, and that the warre shalbe brought to stād altogether vpon artillerie, I saye, that this opinion is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together false: and so alwaies shalbe taken of those, who according to the auncient vertue will occupie their armies: for that he that will make a good armie, it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him with exercises, eyther fained, or trew, to accus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome
<pb facs="tcp:176553:38"/> his men to geue the charge on the enemy, and to come to the swordes poincte with him, and to the gras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine by the boosome: and he ought to grounde him selfe more vpon the footemen, then vpon the horsemen. And when he shall ground him selfe vpon the footemen, and vpon the foresayde maners, the artillerie becommeth altogether vnprofitable. For that with more facelity, the footemen in aproching néere the enemie, may auoide the shot of the artillery, then they were able in olde time to auoide the violence of Elifants, of cartes full of hookes &amp; of other straunge incoūters, which y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Romaine foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men incountered withall, against which, alwayes they founde the remedie, and so muche more easelie they should haue found against this, the shorter that the time is, in the which the artillery may hurte thée, then the same was, in the which the Elifantes &amp; the cartes were able to hurte: for as much as they in the middest of the fighte, disordered men, these onelye before the fighte doo trouble men: the which impediment the footemen ease<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly auoide, either with gowing couered by the nature of the situacion, or with falling downe vpon the grounde, whē they shoote: the which also by experience hath béens séene not to be needefull, in especially to be defended frō greate ordinaunce, the which cannot in such wyse be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled, because if they gowe highe, they touche thée not, &amp; if they gow lowe, they will not come néere thée. Then the armies being come to hande strokes, this is more cleare, then the lighte, that neyther the greate, nor the littell can after hurt thée: for that if the same, which hath the artillery, be before, it becommeth thy prisoner, if it behind, it hurteth the friende before thée. Againe on the backe it cannot hurte thee after such sorte, that thou art not able to gow to winne it, and it commeth to follow the sayd effect. Nor this nede not much disputacion: for that there hath bene séene the example of the Suizers, whoo at Nauara in the yere of our Lorde .1513. without
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:176553:38"/> artillerie, and withoute horse, wente to incounter the Frenche army furnished with artillery within their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tresse, and they ouerthrew thē withoute hauing any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment thereby: and the reason is (besides the thinges told afore) that the artillerie mynding to haue it worke, hath néede to be garded eyther of a wall, or of ditches, or of banckes. And when it lacketh one of these gardes, it is taken, or becommeth vnprofitable, as it happeneth when it is defended with men, for when they chaunce to be in a battaile, and in the fight on the lande, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be occupied by flanke, but in the same maner, that the antiquitie occupied the instrumentes to shoote, which they placed oute of the squadrons, for that they shoulde fight out of the orders, and alwayes whē eyther of horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or of other they were charged vpon, their refuge was behinde the legions: he that otherwise maketh ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compte of them, hath no skill, and trusteth vpon a thing, which easely may deceyue him. And though the Turke by meanes of artillerie, against the Sophi and the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan, hath had victory, it hath not happened through other meanes, then through the feare that the horsemen were put in by the straunge rumor thereof. Therefore to make an ende of this discourse, I cōclude, that the artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie is profitable in an army, when the auncient vertue is mingled therewith, but withoute the same, against a puisant army, it is moste vnprofitable.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="29" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176553:39"/>
            <head>
               <hi>¶</hi> Of Muynes and placing of poulder vnder grounde, wherewith inuinsible fortresses, by fire maye be ruignated, when ordinaunce cannot bee brought vnto them. Capi. xxviiii.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He better and greater</hi> quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetie of poulder which is put in a Caue that is made to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe a Forte or Castel, the greater vndoutedlie shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be the effecte thereof: which caue is best to be made a good waye within the ground, and in a harde place, to the intent that when the same is shutte &amp; well walled vp, the fire be not able easely to haue any other waye oute, then in ouerthrowing the thing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to be ruyned, for as much as if the aire, &amp; the fire in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> roome of that inclosed place, may haue meanes to breathe out, the force therof wilbe of no effecte. Also it wold be takē héede of, that the caue be not by no other meanes marde, so that the fire maye breake oute:: for which cause, it ought to be made, with the beginning thereof somewhat distant frō the place, that you minde to ouerthrow: to the intent that in making thereof, the men of the same place doo not issue oute to let you, nor perceiue the certaine place of the hurt, to be able to prouide for it, and to make countermuynes to let the fire brethe oute and pas with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute anie effecte, whereby all youre coste and laboure may become vaine, Moreouer they make these muines the moste naroweste and moste crookedest that maye be, and in especially néere the very place that is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poincted to be ouerthrowen, and therefore vnder such a place there muste be digged a hole that maye be at
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:176553:39"/> least thrée yardes high or more, and twoo yardes broade and that the entrie vnto it bée vndergrounde in the maner, as by this presente figure you maye sée descri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bed.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut of a cave and tunnel containing barrels of explosives</figDesc>
               <p>THE FOVNDATION ON THE MVINE DISCOVERED</p>
               <p>THE PLACE OF GREATEST EFFECTE</p>
            </figure>
            <p>And in this to put barrelles with their heades knoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked oute full of good strong pouder, betwéene which you must also strawe pouder ynough vpon the bordes wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on they stande, laying to it a good great matche made of cotton, boyled in vinegre, brimstone, and Saltpeter, whiche muste bée well roled in good serpentine pouder well dried in the sunne: and hauing laide it to the place, you must make a trayne of pouder vpon it, euen to the going out, so that it may bée couered therwith: placing it in pipes of earth or tronkes of woode in the place of the entrie therof: &amp; that done, you must wall it vp moste strongly, laying ouerthwarte great blockes of okes or other woode: so that with those &amp; with the wall, if maye bée strong to resiste the furye of the fire, as muche as is possible: and the entrie in suche maner made vp and fortefied, when you shall thincke it time to bring the
<pb facs="tcp:176553:40"/> effecte to pas, to destroye the aduersaries, or to make a ruine, you may cause the trayne to be set on fire, where you shall sée a maruaylous and horrible effecte followe. More aboute this matter I néede not to declare sauing that if it shoulde chaunce the muyne to be made in a stonie place, where the stones will fall downe, that then the best is to vnderproppe them with pipes of wood fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led full of pouder.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The maner how to make trombes or trunkes of fyre, as well to assaulte as to defende a breache, or gate, and to set a fyre a towne or Campe or anye thing else. Cap. xxix.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irst cause a cane of good wood</hi> to be made at the corners as big as a mans thigh and the length of an ell, after such sort that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hole therof be as wide that a man maye thrust in his naked arme, and cause that the bottom of the sayd trūcke be made in suche wise with a litle hole, that the staffe of a partesan may enter into it, and so to bée made fast ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, binding the sayde truncke with yron wyre at both endes, and in the middest for more suerty that it breake not, through y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fury of the fire. Then fil it with this mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture here following. Take serpentine pouder iiij. pound rosen i. pound, cāphere half a poūde, beaten glas iiij. on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; mingle euerything together, then begin to fil and put in the trumbe a handefull of serpentine pouder vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixte, nexte a handefull of the foresaide mixture, after a litle pouder, then a stoppell of cotten wet in oyle of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neper, and put in vppon the sayde cotton as you haue done at the firste, that is to saye pouder, and then mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:176553:40"/> &amp;c. And thus you must doo till you haue filled it full, stamping in the stuffe alwayes lightyly, and if for lacke of gineper oyle you wet the cotten in <hi>aqua vitae,</hi> it is very good putting after euery quantitie of pouder a litle quick siluer, then when it is full, put in the mouthe some good pouder, making it a single couer of parchement boūd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with packthréed, &amp; with a litle hole in the middest of the parchement, wherin you muste put a matche made with gunpouder, the whiche easyly and quickelye with your common matche may kindle the fyre, being come to the face of the enemie: whiche is an excellente thing for the fight on the sea, or for to disorder a band of horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut of 3 trombes</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Howe to make bottels or pottes offyre worke to throwe into shippes or among men that are in battelraye. Cap. xxx.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:176553:41"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch earthē bottels or pottes</hi> as is commonly vsed to kepe vineger or oyle and such like is best for this purpose, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che muste be filled with this composition: serpentine pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der twoo partes, rosen one parte, pitche one parte, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting moste finelie, all these things together in a morter, then take turpentine, &amp; a litle gineper oyle, or linséede oyle, and mingel them therewith in a caudron vpon the fire with a sticke of a yarde long, and fill the bottels half full of this foresayde receipt, that done, take serpentine pouder one parte, rosen one part, brimstone halfe a part, pytche halfe a part, and of this last mixture the bottels or pottes must be filled vp: thē in the mouthes of them there must bée put some good pouder, to the intent that with the matche it maye quickely kindle the fire: which bottels or pottes serue well to throwe into a towne or out of a towne amōg enemies, for that the fire of them breaking out flieth all abroade and burneth most horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly where it lighteth, but good héede must be taken that it be first well kindeled before it bée throwen, in espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if it be caste from aboue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>¶</hi> An other composition of fire vvorke. Cap. xxix.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ause as manye earthen bottels or pottes to bée made as you liste to haue, whiche must bée as it were but halfe baked, then fill them with this mixture following, serpentine pouder thrée partes, Saltpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one parte, turpentine halfe a parte, pytche halfe a parte, brimstone one parte, baye Salte halfe a parte,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:176553:41"/> and when you will throwe them, set them on fire and sée that they bée well kendled.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Balles of mettell to throwe among men in battelraye or otherwise, which breaking shall doo wonderfull hurte. Cap. xxxii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O dissorder and to make the</hi> enemies to giue place, there maye also bée prouided, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine hollow balles of mettel as bigge as small boules, and a quarter of an inche thicke, caste in mouldes and made of thrée partes of brasse and one of tinne: but the brasse oughte to bée molte before the tinne be put to it, whiche balles filled halfe full of fine corne pouder, and the other halfe full, of serpentine pouder mingled with rosen beaten into pouder, so that for thrée partes of serpentine poulder there be one part of rosen, and then puting in the mouthes of the holes of them a litle fine corne pouder to make the rest to fire the sooner and after being fired and throwen, they will breake and flye into a thousande peeces, and both hurt &amp; kyll whom so euer is néere or aboute them. Wherefore they are verye good to throwe ouer the walles into a towne or fortresse, or into a campe, to hurte and to giue a terrour to those that are within: but these balles after they are fired and well kindeled, and hauing blowen a litle, must be quickly throwen, least they hurt such as would hurle them: and therefore the experience of one, ought first to bée made in a close place, to sée howe long it will tary before it breake, &amp; the holes that it will make in diuers places, wherby the other maye the better bee knowen howe to be vsed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:176553:42"/>
               <head>¶ The maner how to prepare pottes and balles of fyreworke to throwe with hande. Cap. xxxiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the world there hath bene</hi> alwayes men of such preng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant wittes, that haue excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in sundry and infinite in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, as well for the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uegarde of humane bodies as also for the destruction of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> like. By whose helpe there haue béene Capitaines, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che imitating their coūselles haue caused their footemen to carie in their handes, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne earthen pottes and balles, filled full of a certayne composition of pouder, or some vnctius liquor, apte to take fire quicke quicklye: with the whiche incountering the enemies in battaile at hande, haue vigorously whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led those among them, for to prooue, whether with suche meanes they might bée able not onely to disorder them, but also to make them giue place, and to ouerthrowe them: for as muche as suche fyreworkes will maruay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously hurte the enemies not onelye with the smooke of them, but also a great deale and muche more with the horrible and vnquenchable burning of thē, so that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by suche men haue alwayes had moste happye successe, with moste glorious laude and prayse. These fyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes are made in this wise: Take as many earthen pottes or bottelles as you liste, caused to bée made for this purpose, either baked or vnbaked whiche ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no matter, so that the moistenesse of the earth bée dried vp: and these muste bée filled halfe full of serpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine pouder, and somewhat more: and the same pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der muste bée mingled with pytche and brimstone bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to pouder to the quantity of the thirde parte there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:176553:42"/> then there muste be put vpon it a finger thicknes of hogges grease, to the intente that it maye make the fire to dure the lenger and it being in this maner ordered, there must be made a hole into it and a péese of gunpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred matche put therein, with a littell good poulder, and firing it, and holding it so long till it be well kendeled, you shall then throwe it. Also there is made a liquide composition in a cauloron, wherin is put hogges grease, oyle of stones, brimstone, saltepeter twise refined, <hi>aqua vitae,</hi> pytche, turpentine and some serpentine pouder: &amp; the pitche, the brimstone, and the Saltepeter being li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quide, putting thereto the grease, the turpenline, the oile, and the pouder ouer the fire, all muste be sturred and mingled together very well in an earthen pot, or some other thing prepared for the same purpose with a sticke, to the intente that it maye the better incorporate: and then it muste be couered aboute with good pouder, that it maye fire the easelier when you will haue it. And that done, you may occupie it when you wil, and whorle it either with a sling, or with a corde tied vnto it, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise with the hande as you shall thincke best: also of this composition theyr maye bée filled certaine littell purses of linnen clothe, which being bounde about with a corde wilbe fashioned lyke a ball: and these maye bée whorled or shotte oute of trunkes of fire, or otherwise as shall please him that maketh them. Also with this cōposition maye bée annointed whatsoeuer a man wold haue quicklye burnte, as Gates of Tounes, bridges of wood, cartes, monicions, and such like, for that it is a matter that will sone kendell and set a fire any thing, and also able to maintaine it: moreouer littel balles thereof maye be tyed to the heades of dartes to throwe among the enemyes, or where one wold haue any thing fired.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:176553:43"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut depicting pots of fireworks</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>¶</hi> Howe to make balles of wilde fire, to shoote in ordinaunce or to throwe with handes. Cap. xxxiiij.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake serpentine pouder fiue</hi> partes, Saltepeter refined thrée partes, brimstone twoo partes, Rasapina one parte, Camphere halfe a part, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine halfe a parte, halfe a part of glas grossely beaten, baye Salte halfe a part, half a part of oyle of stones, and oyle of linte séede, as muche of the one as of the other, <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> half a part, and all these things being mingled together very well, take thē a péece of canuas as bigge as you will make the ball and make it like vnto a purse, and fill it with the sayde mixture, and then make twoo or three holes therein with a rounde yron somewhat bigger then a bod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:176553:43"/> and put in euery hole a litle sticke.</p>
               <p>And it is to bee vnderstande that this foresayde mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may bée also made vpon the fyre in a cauldron, and the balles that are made thereof must bée rouled in ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine pouder, and then in the mixture, often times co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering them with Toe, well plaistered on, of a good thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenesse, then when they shalbe a litle dried, take the said stickes out of the holes, and fil them halfe full of serpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine pouder, and the other halfe with corne pouder, and giuing fire to the saide balles, and throwing them amōg the enemies, they will do maruaylous &amp; wonderfull hurte. For that the sayde balles will burne within the water, so that falling vpon the armour of soudiours, water cannot quenche them nor any thing else, except aboundaunce of myre or durte. And adding to the saide mixture that is vns<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d halfe a parte of beaten glas and halfe a parte of baye Salte, you maye fill a trumbe therwith after the maner as I haue taught a litle afore.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>¶</hi> To trime Targettes with fireworke to assaulte, or to defende a breache. Cap. xxxv.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Et pipes of brasse as manye as</hi> you liste, and nayle them vpō a target, either sixe viij. or x. and fil the sayde pypes full of the forsaide mixture vnsod, &amp; order the pypes after suche sort that they fire not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but one after an other, so y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> when one is almost bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned oute, the same maye gyue fire to an other by a litle pype as small as ones finger, that muste go from the bottome thereof to the mouthe of an other, and so successiuelye to all, whiche shall continue a long tyme, but the sayde target must
<pb facs="tcp:176553:44"/> be couered with blacke buckeram that the fyreworke bée not perceyued and the giuing of fire the one to the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ To make an other kinde of fireworke. Cap. xxxvi.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake willowe coles, Saltpeter, <hi>aqua vitae,</hi> brimstone, pitche, rosapina, Camphere, oyle of stones, <hi>vernice liquide,</hi> turpentine as much of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> one as the other, mingling e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thing together, &amp; thē take a litle purse of canuas, &amp; all it full of serpentine pouder, &amp; couer the purse all ouer with the foresayde mixture of a good thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenesse, and with as muche Toe as you shall thinke good, and then make a hole that maye go to the middest of the balle, whiche muste bée filled full of pouder, so that therby all the composition therof with a matche maye be set on fyre when you liste.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Howe to make a mixture in stone that shall kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle fire with water or spittel. Cap. xxxvii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His stone is very necessary for a Captain to giue fire to his gunners, when through foule wether, all their matches shoulde happen to go oute, and where they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not kindle thē againe because of the raine. First take vnslaked lime one parte, Tutia alessandrina vnprepared one parte, Saltpeter very well refined one part, quicke brimstone twoo partes, Cāphere twoo parts calamite stone one parte: All these thinges muste bée well beaten and sifted, and bounde harde together with a péece of new linnen cloth, &amp; put into a cople of earthen cuppes, suche as Goldesmithes vse to melte in, the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:176553:44"/> mouthes of whiche muste bée ioyned together and faste bounde with yron wyre, and daubed ouer with <hi>lutum sapientia</hi> that it breathe not out, and then dried a litle, till it become yelowe, that done, put it into a forneys where they burne bricke or earthen vessels, and let it tarye therin as long as the bricke or earthen vessels be a baking, and then taking it out, you shal sée it made like vnto a brickestone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ To make an other kinde of stone to kindle fire with water or spittell. Cap. xxxviii.</head>
               <p>TAke Camphere three partes, Saltepeter well refined twoo partes, vnslaked lime twoo partes brimstone twoo partes, all these thinges (being well beaten together, and put into a cople of goldesmithes melting cuppes well stopped with <hi>lutum sapientia</hi>) must then bée baked in a forneys, and when the earthen vessels bée taken oute, this shall also bée made.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Howe to make lutum sapientia. Cap. xxxix.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake of the best white</hi> pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters earth that you can gette, for in one place there is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then in an other, that is to saye, of that whiche can best endure the fire, as suche as they make pottes of in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua,</hi> and likewise in Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye: for it is of suche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that the Pottes, whiche bée made of it, and wherein that they dresse
<pb facs="tcp:176553:45"/> their meate, may also serue to found metalles in. Take then of the beste, and specially if it must serue for a thing that hath néede to be long vpon a greate fire, otherwise, take suche as you can get. There is founde of it, that is of a graye colour, as the common sorte is, and also there is white, that men vse in some place of <hi>Vicence,</hi> which is like loaues of <hi>Gispom,</hi> or plaister, and is called of the Italians <hi>Florette de Chio.</hi> Wée here in Englande vppon the vse thereof, may geue it what name we will. Potters vse of it in Venise, for to whit the dishes, and other thinges, before they vernishe or pollish them.</p>
               <p>There is also founde of it that is rodde, as in <hi>Apulia,</hi> where there is greate quātetie, and that they call Boale, and is the very same that some Apoticares doo sell for Boale Armenick, &amp; the Venecians vse of it, for to paint redde the forefrontes of their houses with lime, bricke, and Vermillion, couering it afterwarde with oyle of line. This redde earth is the fattest, and the clammiest of all the rest, and therefore it cleaueth soonest by the fire, if it be not tempered with some other substance. And because that all the sayde earthes be to fatte, the one more than the other, therefore menne put to them some leane substaunce. Nowe, if you take of that of ashe coloure, whiche is moste commen, and the least fatty, you maye compose and make it in this maner. Take of the saide earth foure partes, of cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers floxe or shearing, one part, ashes that haue ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in a buck, or other, halfe a parte, drie horse dung, or the dung of an Asse, one part. If you will make it par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiter, put to it a fewe stamped brickes, and sparkes of yron: let all these thinges be well stamped, and sifted, that is to saye: the earthe the ashes, the horse dung, the brickes, and the sparkes of yron: than mingle all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and make it into earth, and make a bedde thereof, vppon the whiche you shall caste by littel and littel, the floxe, as equally as you can. This done, powre to it wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:176553:45"/> styring it well first with a sticke, &amp; then with a pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let broade at the ende. And when all is well incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together as you woulde haue it, laye it vppon some great borde, and beate it well, and that a good space with some great staffe or other instrument of yron, mingling and stearing it well, for the lenger you beate it, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is. By this meane you shall haue a very good claye, for to lute or clay, and ioyne violles, flagons of glasse to still with, and bottels of gourdes for stilling, and other great thinges, as fournesses and such like. But he that wil make it with more ease, let him put the earth onely, the floxe, and the horse dong, with a fewe ashes. Some put no horse dong to it, and some no floxe, according to the purpose that they make it for. For to stop and close vp the mouthes of stilling glasses, or violles, to the intent they take no vent on the fire, the sayde clay will be very good: neuerthelesse men put to it twoo partes of quicke lime, and the whites of Egges, and then it will be surer to let nothing vent oute but the glasse it selfe. All kinde of clay or earth would bée kéept moiste, and réedy dressed for him that will occupye it continually, but it must not bée kept to watery, nor yet left to drie, for then it would serue for nothing, séeing that after it is once hardened, a man can not dresse it any more to do any good withall.</p>
               <p>And when you put water to it, it is mollified by litle &amp; litle aboue, and is as it were a sauce, but within remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth harde, and if you put to muche water to it, you marre it vtterlye. Therfore, when you sée that it begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to waxe drie, féede it a new litle and litle with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, styring it till it bée well, and so shall you make it perfecte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ How to make certayn fireworke to tye at the poinctes of pikes or horsemen staues. Cap. xl.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:176553:46"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or to assaulte or to defende a breache, and also to worke some policie in the nighte against the enemies, it is sometimes good to tye at the poinctes of pikes or launces, certayne canes like vnto squibbes made of paper vpon a forme of wood as long as the breadeth of a shéete of paper, filled full of serpentine pouder, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeste the whiche muste bée mingled litle péeces or crummes of pitche, of brimstone, graynes of baye salt, filinges of yron, and beaten glasse, arsinic, cristall bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to péeces, and suche like, and after they are closed vp, and tied faste at one of the endes, this composition muste bée well beaten into them, with there owne for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes or mouldes: vnto euery one of which there must be put a good matche sod in Saltepeter and Gunnepouder, and then well dried, and fastening them to staues, after such sorte that the issue of the fire bée tourned towardes the aduersaries, when you thinke good, you or some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may fire them: wher you shall then sée the fire blow out twoo yardes long, which in the night will séeme ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible: but in a calme wether, or at least when the winde is in the faces of the enemies they are best to be vsed.</p>
               <p>And moreouer for the fighte on the sea, they are moste excellente.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of pikes and spears tipped with squibbs</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:176553:46"/>
               <head>¶ Howe to make diuers compositions of fireworkes. Cap. xli.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very thing that will quickly</hi> burne, and that by some pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per vertue is apte to multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie fire, and maītaine it, may be put in firye compositions: for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> in effecte of such thinges they are made: of whiche thinges there are some that are minerall, as Brimstone, and the oyle therof, and salte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter, &amp; some other substaunces, hot, drie, &amp; thin, &amp; some vnctius, as grease, and all sortes of oyles: some very dry, as pitch or wood: and of these there be some natural, and some artificiall: But nowe leauing to séeke suche diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of theyr compositions, among as many thinges as well old as new y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I know, I haue found only these: out of whiche I haue chosen some of the notablest, spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially these, that for to make them, there muste be takē Rosen, Alchitrean, quicke Brimstone, tartar, sarcocolla, Saltepeter, and oyle of stones, and of euery one some parte, but double so much of vnslaked lime, &amp; al must be compounded with the oyle of egges: and put into a ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel of glasse or of earth that is leaded, &amp; couered very wel: putting it after vnder hot dung for a moneth: thē taking it from thens and setting it ouer a softe fire, the vessell being well stopped, it muste be melted: which done, the licor thereof may be put into hollowe staues, or in year- then bottells, or other vessells made of purpose: vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of which, must bée put a péece of a gunpoudred matche, in the middest with some gunpouder also, to the intent that they maye the easelier fire.</p>
               <p>Also there may be made an other sorte of fireworke after this maner: taking Brimstone, or oyle of Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone
<pb facs="tcp:176553:47"/> yf it maye be had, oyle of stones, or of the fame stonye Oyle of Iuniper, Saltepeter very well refined: and for euery porcion of suche thinges, fiue of aspallto: and moreouer goosegrease, pure pitche, vernis, pouder of pigeons dunge, and so muche <hi>aqua vitae,</hi> that maye throughly moyste all the foresayde thinges: which then muste be putte into a vessell of glasse, and the mowthe thereof well stopped with waxe, and then put vnder a hot dunghill .xxv. or .xxx. dayes: and after to make it the better incorporate, it wolde be set ouer a softe fire: and that done, this composition maye be put into hollowe staues, or yearthen pottes or like vessells to be throwen with the hande: also there maye be taken a bullet of stone with a ring fastened therein, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto wolde be tied a corde of a yarde long: and aboute the same stone, putting Toe imbrewed with the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayde composition, or ells péeses of linnen clothe all to rayed therewith, whiche tiring, when it is well kend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, maye then be throwen. Also balles of this compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition maye be shotte in péeses of ordinaunce, or a stone that hath a ring of yron fastened in it, to the which ring may be tied a péece of a rope stéeped and sod in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayde composition, or ells a littell bagge full thereof, which maye be shotte or throwen as one liste. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer balles of this, being made with linnen clothe as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is shewed, may be caste with all sortes of slinges which way one will.</p>
               <p>Also there is made an other composition in this maner, with vernice liquide, oyle of quicke Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone, and oyle of the yelkes of egges, turpintine oyle, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niper oyle, linséede oyle, and <hi>olium saxum,</hi> or oyle of stones, and haulfe as muche of <hi>aqua vitae</hi> as all the saide compositions: and also as muche pouder of bayes fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie beaten as will suffise to thicken all, with as muche more Saltepeter: and all these thinges muste be put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in a vessell of glasse, or some vessell of yearth lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:176553:47"/> with a littell mouthe, which with waxe muste be so stopped that it vente not: and this must bée kepte after thrée monethes in hotte dung, to putrifie, remouing it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye moneth fowre or fiue times, and shaking it toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euery time: and this matter being broughte in such wise, when you will occupie it, it is requisite that you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noinct the same thing that you will vse, or to put thereof into that vessell, where you will haue the fire to worke: for that the same fire is suche, that putting thereto some gunnepouder, or a gunnepoudred matche, it wil straight waye kendell: and it is so vnquencheable, that it bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth till hée, or the thing that it lighteth on, bée alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether consumed: and if this composition fired, chaunce to be throwen and lighte vpon armur, it will make it so glowing redde in suche sorte, that he that hath it on his backe, shalbe constrained to put it of, if he will not be burnte to death.</p>
               <p>Also there is made an other sorte: and it is a moste thinne liquor apte to fire, with the whiche if in the canicular daies a péece of woodde, or other thing apte to burne bée anoincted, the heate of the Sunne is then able to set it on fire, and to burne it: and so sone as it is touched with fire, it kendeleth incontinente, and is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quencheable: excepte it be chooked vp with sande, or wet with very stale vrin, or moste strong vineger: also it will burne in the water: the making, whereof is in this wise: there muste be taken Camphire, oyle of quicke Brimstone, oyle of turpentine, oyle of dunge, oyle of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neper, oyle of stones, oyle of lintesede, alchitrean, colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fonia, moste finelye beaten, oyle of egges, pitche, goose grease, Saltpeter, and as much <hi>aqua vitae</hi> as all the rest of the composition, and as muche arsinic, tartar, and armoniack salte, as the eighte parte of altogether.</p>
               <p>Which thing muste bée put into a glasse or pot wel stop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and then set to putrefie in a hotte dunghill for the space of twoo monethes: and after al the forsayd thinges
<pb facs="tcp:176553:48"/> muste bée destilled with a gentle fire: where within viii. houres, there will come of those thinges a moste suttill liquor, into the whiche putting then so muche oxedung dried in an ouen and moste finelye beaten to pouder, as maye make it so thicke as sope or somewhat thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: and after minding to occupye it, the thing that is to bée burnte, muste bée annoincted therewith: and this also the Sunne will set on fyre, and burne what so euer is néer it.</p>
               <p>Also there is an other composition of fyre, that anye thing that is annoincted therewith, will maruaylouslye burne and fire with weting of raine, or otherwise: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che to make, there must bée taken new whitelime made of flinte, calamite made to pouder by fyre, vitrioll grosse beaten the twoo and thirteth parte, Saltepeter refined eyght partes: and as muche Camphere as all the foresayde thinges: oyle of quicke brimstone: oyle of turpentine, Salte armoniacke, by waighte as muche as the vitrioll, and as muche tartar and baye Salte: Salte of vrin, <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> made of strong wine as much as all the rest of the composition: the which things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded together, muste bée put like as the otherwere, into a great glasse well stopped that it breath not oute: and then it muste bée set in a whote dounghill for twoo or thrée monethes, remoouing the glasse and chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the doung at leaste euerye tenne dayes, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that the same matter maye ripen well, and bée like vnto a liquor all of one thing: the whiche after oughte to be boyled so muche vpon a softe fire, that all the oyly humidetie, and other moystenesse that is in it, maye va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por awaye, and the rest to become drie and stonye: and when it is drie and stony, breaking the glasse &amp; taking it out, it must bée grounde to pouder: the whiche when it is to be occupied, must be strawed vpon the place that is dressed for the same purpose, so y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it being rayned vpō or any maner of waies wet, will kindle &amp; fall on a fire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:176553:48"/>
               <head>¶ How to make a girdle for Souldiours or Fisshers wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may go in the water and passe ouer a riuer without either bridge or bote. Cap. xlii.</head>
               <p>THis Girdle oughte to be made according to the fashion of the figure next following, and of such lether that muste be dressed in like sorte, as the same is where with footebals are made: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto a pipe muste be fastened like vnto a baggepipe, so that the girdle, when it is girte about a Soudiour vpon his armour, maye be blowen full of winde: by helpe whereof, he maye then safelye passe ouer a riuer, going through the same, howe déepe so euer it be, where he shal not sinke in the water, further then from the girdle stéede downe warde: whiche for men of warre, is verye commodious and a most necessarie thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of a girdle used for flotation</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="41" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176553:49"/>
            <head>¶ How to write, and cause the same that is writen to be read a farre of without sending anye message. Cap. xli.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen a Capitain were so besie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> of enemies in a towne or fortresse that no man coulde come vnto him, or be sent frō him with letters, wherby his minde, or the distresse and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience that hée is in, might of his friendes bée vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstande. Yet his minde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing written, maye of thē not withstanding in the night be read, as farre of as a lighte can then be séene, and by daye, as farre as a burning glas can caste the sunne, or a hat or any other such like marke maye perfectlye bée decerned, so that the order therin bée firste knowen and agréed vpon betwéen both parties. The maner in doing it in the night, is thus: hée that giueth the aduise, muste holde his letter in the one hande wherin his minde is réedy written, and one lighte or ij. lightes in the other hande, and the other that should reade and copy the same, ought to haue paper, and penne and inke with this a b c, etc. herefollowing, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstande:
<table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>a</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>b</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>c</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>d</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>e</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>f</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>g</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>h</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>i</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>k</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>l</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>m</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>n</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>o</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>q</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>r</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>s</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>t</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>v</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>w</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="11">
                        <hi>this part of letters vvith 1. lighte,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi> &amp; </hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell cols="10">
                        <hi>this part vvith tvvoo lightes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>And for the plainer vnderstanding hereof, it is to bée noted that the first parte of the letters are shewed with one lighte, and the seconde parte beginning at, <hi>M,</hi> are signified with two lightes, and euerye letter of the a b c muste bée vnderstande, and knowen by the nomber or often shewing and hiding of the sighte or lightes: As for example, if this worde, <hi>Man,</hi> were to be written,
<pb facs="tcp:176553:49"/> because <hi>M</hi> is the first letter standing in the second part, <hi>M</hi> muste be signified by twoo lightes shewed once, and then hidden, and staied so long as maye be thoughte that he that doeth copye after the lighte so seuerallye shewed, and the number diligently marked, maye haue conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient time to write <hi>M:</hi> then one lighte being shewed once, and so hidde and staide, <hi>a</hi> muste be written: for that <hi>a</hi> is the firste letter in the firste parte: and againe twoo lightes being shewed twise and stayde, <hi>n,</hi> oughte to be written, because <hi>n</hi> is the second letter in the second part: whiche done, there shalbe written <hi>Man.</hi> And thus by marking well the number of shewing, hyding and stay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the lighte or lightes, the letter that thereby is signified, maye moste easely be vnderstand and perceyued. So that after this sorte, there maye be expressed and written what so euer a man liste.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:176553:50"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the Britons the auncient inhabitauntes of this Isle (for lacke of skillfull men of vvarre of their ovvne, being afraied of the Franki, &amp; Burgundi, vvhiche vvere certaine Barberous natiōs, vvho at the time ouer ran, spoiled, &amp; possessed Frāce) caused the Germaine people called Angly to come to ayde and defende them, by vvhose procurement the Angly vnder Vortiger their King, taking vpō the the same enterprise, after they had ones defended them, did then incontinente driue them out of this Islande, remaining here themselues to inhabite: and after their name called it England: euē as also of later daies, the like chaūce happened to the Greekes, by calling in the Turckes to helpe them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their enemies. VVhich exāples, vvith innumerable like being vvell considered, do most manifestlie shevv, hovv daungerous &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitius it is for a Prince and his Realme, to be driuen to truste to the seruice of straungers, for lacke of sufficient skillfull men of their ovvn for their defence. VVherfore sithens my intent in setting fourth this booke of Martial affaires, hath beene onely to the ende to declare my good vvill, to haue my naturall countriemen not to bee inferiour to anye in vvarlike knovvledge, but rather to excell in the same, vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by vvithout aide or helpe of any forein nation, vvee may alvvaies bee most renovvmed and famous, I shall beseeche all gentil readers, for this my labour done for their cōmodities, to iudge and reporte ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of accordingly. And although my doinges herin, be not correspondēt to my desire, nor to the satisfactiō of euery mās minde (vvhich vvere impossible) yet my trust is, that some neuerthelesse by diligente rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding therof, and imitating the example of Lucullus, (vvho chiefelye by studie of like bookes, in very shorte space, became one of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantest and vvorthiest vvariour of all the Romanes,] may if they list, take commoditie and profite, vvhereby the knovvledge in vvarres, may of such as neuer haue bene trayned in them, be the more easyly gotten and attayned. For vvhich cause, my indeuour and trauayle ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken herein, for to profit this our common vveale, deserueth not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to be despised, seeing that the most verteous life, and gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Alexander Seuerus Emperour of Rome, vvith manye other Princes, and common vveales, could not, being negligēt in this kinde
<pb facs="tcp:176553:50"/> of studie and practis therof, saue or defende them selues, from moste shamefull endes, &amp; miserable deathes vvherin fortune vvas not to be blamed, but only their folly &amp; ignoraunce, for hauing neuer thought in time of tranquilitie and pease that it coulde chaunge into aduersi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and trouble: the vvhich is a common faulte of men, not to make accompte in fayre vveather, of the tempest to come.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:176553:51"/>
            <head>¶ The table of the additions.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Perfecte rule to bring men into a square battell, of what nomber so euer they bée. Fol. ij.</item>
               <item>To knowe howe many men may march in a rancke, &amp; at a sudddaine to bring thē into a fowersquare battayle, so y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> their Ansigne, maye come to bée in the middest. Fol. iij.</item>
               <item>Howe to ordayne a nomber of men or an armie into a battayle, like vnto a wedge, or thrée square, so that it maye be apt to marche with the poincte therof toward the enemies. Fol. vi.</item>
               <item>To make the battayle called the shéeres, whiche in olde time they vsed to set against the Triangle. Fol. vij.</item>
               <item>What auantage it is to order mē in a triangle battayle against the enemie, that knoweth not howe to make the battayle called the Shéeres to set againste it, ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially where there is as many men of the one parte as of the other. Fol. viii.</item>
               <item>To bring a nomber of men or an army, into a battayle, whiche in olde time was called a Sawe. Fol. ix.</item>
               <item>To fashion a battayle of a nomber of men or an armye like vnto twoo Triangles ioyned together, so that they may bée apte to march with a corner thereof towarde the enemies. Fol. x.</item>
               <item>What is best to bée done where the ordinaunce of the enemies being shot into the Armye hath slayne many men. Fol. xi.</item>
               <item>Howe to chaunge with spéede an armye, that is, in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telray fouresquare, into a Triangle fashion, without disordering the first ranckes, and without perill of cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion. Fol. xiii.</item>
               <item>Of the perfecte forme or fashion of strong places. Fol. xvi.</item>
               <item>The strongest and perfectes fashion of all other for the building of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cortin or wall of a town or fortresse. Fol. xviii.</item>
               <item>An example of the quadrante forme to prooue that it
<pb facs="tcp:176553:51"/> causeth debilletie and weakenesse. Fol. xxii.</item>
               <item>Of the nature of Saltepeter, and the manner howe to make and refine it. Fol. xxiij.</item>
               <item>The manner howe to make all sortes of Gunpouder. Fol. xxvij.</item>
               <item>The manner that is vsed of charging and shooting of ordinaunce. Fol. xxxiii.</item>
               <item>Howe to gette oute quickely the nailes that should hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen by Treason, or otherwyse to be driuen into the toucheholes of ordinaunce. Fol. xxxiiij.</item>
               <item>Howe much the artillery ought to bée estemed of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies nowe adaies, and whether the same opinion of them which is had vniuersally, be true. Fol. xxxiiij.</item>
               <item>Of Muines and placing of Pouder vndergrounde, wherewithe inuinsible Fortresses, by fire maye bée ruignated, when ordinaunce cannot be broughte vnto them. Fol. xxxviij.</item>
               <item>The manner howe to make trombes or trunckes of fire, as well to assaulte as to defende a breache, or gate, and to sette a fire a Towne or Campe, or any thing elles. Fol. xxxix.</item>
               <item>Howe to make bottells or pottes of fireworke to throw into shippes, or among menne that are in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellraye. Fol. xl.</item>
               <item>An other composition of fireworke. Fol. xl.</item>
               <item>Balles of mettell to throwe among men in battelraye or otherwise, whiche breaking, shal doo wonderful hurte. Fol. xli.</item>
               <item>The manner howe to prepare pottes and balles of fire worke to throwe with hande. Fol. xli.</item>
               <item>How to make balles of wilde fire, to shoote in ordinaunce or to throwe with handes. Fol. xlii.</item>
               <item>To trimme Targettes with fireworke to assaulte, or to defende a breache. Fol. xliij.</item>
               <item>To make an other kinde of fireworke. Fol. xliij.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:176553:52"/>
               <item>Howe to make a mixture in stone that shall kendel fire with water or spittell. Fol. xliij.</item>
               <item>To make an other kinde of stone, to kendell fire with water or spittell. Fol. xliiij.</item>
               <item>Howe to make lutum Sapientia. Fol. xliiij.</item>
               <item>Howe to make certaine fireworke, to tye at the poinctes of Pikes or Horsemenstaues. Fol. xlv.</item>
               <item>Howe to make diuers compositions of fireworkes:</item>
               <item>Howe to make a girdell for Souldiours or Fisshers, whereby they may goo in the water and passe ouer a riuer withoute eyther bridge or boote, Fol. xlviij.</item>
               <item>Howe to write, and cause the same that is written to bée redde a farre of, withoute sending anye mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage. Fol. xlviij.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>¶ <hi>The ende.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:176553:52"/>
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London, by VV. VVilliamson: for</hi> Ihon VVight.</p>
            <p>¶ Anno salutis. M.D.LXXIII. Mense. Septembris.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>